and welcome to our quick walk-through of using models in Django, again, we're working through
the Mozilla Developer Network tutorial, so we're in this tutorial about using models.
Now this tutorial has a lot of useful information, so it's designing the local library models,
this is something you should read carefully and understand, hopefully you've had some
data model design before or watched some information about data model design, so we have sort of
authors and books and genres and the language and books and how they're checked out, so
just read all this.
This talks about how we define these models, take from that diagram and turn the models
into Django models, how we add fields to those models, how we add foreign keys, logical keys,
etc., etc., and so just, I'm going through this fast, just I want you to read all that
and what I'm gonna do is jump down to this defining local library models 'cause this
is sort of the work that you've gotta do, so once you understand all that through whatever
way you understand it, we're going to go ahead to our Python Anywhere account and start a
new bash console, and then we're gonna say work on Django 2, pick our virtual environment,
then we're gonna go CD Django projects, I say DJ Tab there, and then local library is
the project, and if we take a look, we've got the catalog, local library is the configuration,
we've been editing these files all along, and so here we are, if you recall, we've run
the SQL light command in previous that we can see what's in here, we're gonna be adding
some new tables, so we're going to edit the file catalog, models.py, I'll use nano to
edit that, and it has something in there, it's exactly as predicted here, and then we're
gonna add, I'm just gonna add one of the models, there's several that we've gotta add, but
for now, I'm just going to paste that one in, and control x, y, enter, and so now if
I do a git status, you can see that I made one small change, okay, so once we've made
this change, this whole concept of make migrations, all make migrations does, it looks at all
the models.py file, and there's some in there already for the administration, which we're
gonna see in the next assignment.
This looks at the models, now this one's gonna detect changes, so oh, there's a new model
in that file, so we have to create what's called a migration, migration is a script
that basically creates new tables, or updates tables, et cetera, so we're gonna run the
make migrations, and then we're gonna actually do the migration, so these are separate, so
the migrations would get, if we were running in production, you might check the migration
into GitHub, and then run migrate both locally, and on your production server, so we'll just
do the migrate right away, and the migrate is what is actually creating the new table,
and we already did kind of a git status, we can see that we got two new files, we'll deal
with those in a second, okay, but now we're gonna run this command right here, sqlite3,
and we're gonna read that database file, so if we take a look at the files, it's this
file, so that is how we do it, so we're in a sqlite command line browser, you can see
how to use this, but .tables, we see this new one, so if you looked at it before, you
saw all these things, but now because we've added this new model file, we have this catalog.genre,
so schema tells us what the shape, copy, paste, so this tells us a SQL create table that would
be necessary to create this, we have a primary key named id, and then a name field, so that's
a pretty simple table, and if we take a look at the migration, that's what we had, we had
this name, which was basically some text, okay, and the id is automatically generated,
that's the primary key that's automatically generated, so that's the way we go, so you
can either hit Ctrl+D or .quit, I'll hit Ctrl+D here, so here we are, and so now we can edit
this again, this time I'll use vi, catalog_models.py, again, learn to use that tab, go to the end
with a zero G, zero capital G, and now I'm just going to kind of blast these things in
here, copy these guys, it'd be better for you to understand this, so one of the problems
that people have, I think, open, open a new line, is people are so much in a hurry to
get through these tutorials, and of course I'm blasting through them too, that you just
type this and you just put it back in without understanding it, and that just means that
you're going to have to come back and you're going to have to actually learn this when
it comes time to writing an application that you're doing yourself, and then the author
model, let's look at these for a little bit of time, I'm just showing you how to do it
here, so you're not wasting too much time watching me on the video, escape colon wq
to save it, if I do a get diff, this is a more prompt here, this little colon, so I've
got a genre model, a book model, a book instance model, and an author model, so those are the
actually, an author model, and then Q gets me out of that, these are basically the models
that represent, in a sense, everything except the language, and so you've got to actually
add the language here, and it's kind of telling you where you're supposed to hook the language
up, what kind of a thing, so you in this challenge, you've got to add the language, so there's
a challenge down here, figure out where to hook it up, read all these models, and then
add a language model and get that right as well, connect it to the right place, again
there's a bunch of stuff that you've got to read, that's unfortunate, so see this thing
about language model, you've got to do this too, I'm not going to do it in this video,
so now that we've got these things done, we're going to run the make migrations again, so
it's going to have two migrations when we're done, I could have done all the edits and
done one migration, but I just wanted to show you, and then I want to do the migrate to
actually create the tables, okay, and so, if I do an SQLite, and I look at .tables,
see now I've got a lot more, I've got like, this genre was there before, but now I've
got like catalog author, and I can say .schema, catalog author, and we see the primary key,
the first name, the last name, date of birth, date of death, and that of course is taken
straight from these things right here, so this is called an object relational mapper,
which takes this author object and then turns it into a set of tables in a database and
does joins automatically, we'll get to all that eventually, so .quit or control D gets
us out of that, so we've seen that, and at that point, we're all done, we've got our
models, we've got our model created, if we are doing this in GitHub, oops, where'd I
just go, where am I, local library, pwd, local library, there I am, so if I do a git status
here, so you can see all the things that have been added in my local library, and then I'm
going to just say git add catalog migration star, because all these added files aren't
there yet, so that's okay, pycache, something you'd never want to add, it just ended up
in that star, so it's okay, git status, so these are the added files, and the catalog
files, and then we're going to commit that, and push it into our git repo, okay, so now
I typed in my password, and so it's all set up, and just for our own sanity, we're going
to give ourselves another tag in our GitHub repo, just so we can keep track of the fact
that, because you might have made a couple of commits, we only made one commit, I did,
because I knew what I was doing, and then we'll upload the tags to GitHub, and so if
I look at GitHub, jangle projects, see we got five commits, that one we just did, and
the other one we just did, so we're going to click on that one, and then we're going
to click on that one, and we're going to click on that one, and then we're going to click
on that one, and then we're going to click on that one, and then we're going to click
the SQLite file, so you go into jangle projects, local library, and dbsqlite, and then you
download it right here, so it downloads that file, and then you end up with this file locally
on your hard drive, and so if you have a command line on your computer, or the SQLite browser
on the computer, you can look at this, and you may have to turn it in as part of your
assignment, so that's how you download the file if you need to do that, okay, so thanks
for listening, and to our little discussion of jangle models.