Hello and welcome to another walkthrough for Django for Everybody.
This is kind of a supplement to tutorial two.
In tutorial two you're playing with models dot py and if you go through the tutorial
they'll have you do a thing and then they'll do another thing and they're kind of showing
you migrations and how the migrations happen.
If you have a mistake, you know, if you make a mistake then you can get to the point where
you need help or whatever and sometimes it's easier to just like wipe out your database.
But if you've added a question or added some choices or built models, you've got to do
all that stuff.
But it's sometimes just easier to redo some of those things.
So I'm going to show you what to do if your model slash database gets messed up and like
your manage dot py make migrations and migrate are not doing what you think or they're giving
you weird errors.
Now if they're getting a syntax error, make sure you do a Python manage py check right
before you declare that your database is messed up.
So let me go into my site.
So here I am now.
Here's all my files.
So just so you so so here I should do it before I declare that the database is a problem.
Manage dot py check and oops oh I messed that up.
I'm in my virtual environment of course.
Okay, so we got no issues now.
So that's good.
So there's I got a couple of commands here.
Let me explain this before I'm going to actually delete these.
I want to show you where the migration I probably showed you this.
So I have a thing called polls to and I got all the polls running.
So this is like in tutorial to the migrations are in files with this with a number and their
Python files.
So if you recall migrations are portable representations of what happens in the database.
And then the migrate creates the file db.sqlite.
So you need if you want to really start over you got to get rid of both the migrations
and the db.sqlite file and then you can start completely fresh if you I mean you can sort
of do parts of them but I'm like if you're messed up here tutorial to it's probably easier
to just get rid of them both.
So at this point my application is going to stop working.
So I get rid of the migrations and then I get rid of my database.
And so at this point the only thing I got that has to do with anything with my database
is a few models dot py files.
And this is where we are editing our code.
And so this polls to models py in my particular example is the code that's going to be effective
because I just because I've got all the versions of running at the same time.
That's why you're seeing this.
So the next thing you do is Python 3 or Python manage py make migrations.
So what make migrations is doing is it's reading all these models dot py files and it's writing
this file.
So I got rid of that file but now if I do an ls you'll see that it's come back and sometimes
you might see an 02 etc. and then you throw it away and you make it fresh and you should
only see an 01 and then you can say Python manage py migrate.
And then that well if you'll do an ls let me control c there if I do an ls you'll see
that there wait a second how come that the dbsqlite3 is zero size.
So I'm going to do Python 3 Python manage sorry my Mac migrate.
So that's reading that's reading these files plus a whole bunch of other ones and actually
creating databases.
And so now if I say ls -l my dbsqlite3 is back and I might have to create a super user
if I if I created a super user account then I'm going to have to create one again right.
And so I'm going to do that vj4e choke csev@umarsh.edu.
I should make my passwords easier to type now at this point things should start working
but again if I created any data like a question or something it was gone it was going at that
moment when I got rid of that database dbsqlite3 it is literally gone.
So it's gone now and away we go and so I and again this is just if you can't seem to make
these migrations or migrates work back up start over and then redo some of the work
and that probably will be a good way to get things done cheers.