so now we're going to talk about the actual template language as I mentioned
before there's more than one templating language we're using the default one and
I think it's actually one of the better ones this whole notion of double curly
braces there's all kind of template templating engines and a lot of them use
these double curly braces sometimes there's a one called mustache because the
curly braces look like a mustache so there's double curly braces you learn it
in Django and you'll find it all kinds of other places I've used it in front end
processing this is back-end processing because we're doing all the substitution
in the back end so there's there's basically a couple things you can do the
double curly braces do substitution and one thing that's cool about this if you
recall I talked about how you have to escape data that came from the user
anything in the double curly braces is automatically escaped as a matter of fact
you have to do something to not escape it because it turns out that 98% of the
time you want to escape data that you're printing out because it doesn't change
what it looks like but it does make sure that it's safe if you add this what this
vertical bar safe afterwards this vertical bar safe afterwards that's like
a modifier I think it's called a filter in Django that says look don't run this
don't run that filter on it to do the HTML entities just do it as is I know
there may be HTML in that but I've taken care of that because I am the
application developer you can call functions like with the code is the
percent curly brace percent and in there you you tend to call a code this is like
code this is like calling a method or a utility code and so the first part of
this is what you're calling and then later you can have some parameters so
this URL says I want to find the URL for the view cat detail and I'm going to take
the number that is the current cat primary key for the cat record and put
that on as the URL as well the author in this case is a and we'll see this later
as a model item and get absolute URL is a method inside that model item you can
have sort of ifs and if then else's and pretty it's kind of Python like which is
nice and that you don't really have to learn new things there is looping code
that's in there like a for loop that we'll talk about in a bit and then there
is X blocks that can be replaced so you can have a template that sort of pulls
in another template and then substitutes in part of it so you can have whole
blocks of substitution not just little strings of substitution and so we'll
talk about each of these in turn so here we go we'll start with a real simple one
and we're not and you'll notice that in this particular simple one we have no
parameters on the command on the URL we so we don't have any parameters here I'm
going back to a non class style just a simple function and I'm not sending a
context the context would be the third parameter on the render call and so I'm
just saying hey and this is what you do when you just have some static HTML that
you don't really need to change anything and so that's what's sitting in here it's
just a simple page there's this thing called a built-in template view class
that sort of does exactly this thing that just grabs a template turns it in
HDB grabs a file turns into an HDB response and sends it back to Django so
that's just a super simple template now here's one we're going to take a
parameter to the context and I'm not taking it from the command line quite yet
I'm just going to make the parameter always be 42 and and the key is this is
a key and this is a value so zap in this case is the key and 42 is the value I
often call this variable context but the fact that's just a mnemonic memory thing
for me context or CTX is what I tend to call it and now I'm passing in the
temple the template this template here the guest guest of HTML template and it
has one little curly brace substitution and remember that does escaping for us
automatically so there's no need to use escape the way there was when we're
doing this by a concatenation that alone is a good reason to use templates and so
this ends up sending out your guess is 42 so this is just really focusing on
what's in that context and how the things come out of the context this name
here zap in the context means pull the thing out of the context under the
string name zap and then it substitutes the results like the 42 so instead of it
saying guess was zap it's your guess is 42 so that's that's really focusing on
the substitution so this is showing us how we do the safe stuff in case you
actually want to pass some HTML into a template and actually want it to render
as HTML not as HTML entities or HTML and any style so we're sending in a
thing that's bold with a B and less than B that's HTML it's got less than and
greater than in it and then we got zap and so you can see that the zap comes
out as 42 it's it's a shame entities but has no special characters but if we
escape text text is the one with the the HTML can end the characters that
automatically escapes it so that you see the less than and greater than in the
browser output escaped less than B bold greater than B right and if you say text
and then add the safe filter to the end of it that says don't escape it and so
then this bold goes right into the HTML document and instead of you seeing the
less than and greater than you're actually seeing the text turn to bold
now usually the bad bad folks that are trying to get into your computer are not
just turning your text to bold they're trying to run JavaScript and all we're
showing here is that whatever less than and greater than would be in that
context value TXT they're going to end up literally in the document and the
browser is going to interpret them as HTML I mean there's just no way that
somehow your browser knows the the HTML that came from your program versus the
HTML that came from a context variable because by the time it gets to the
browser it's all one thing so it doesn't know oh wow that that's dangerous that
came from a variable now by the time the response goes back to the browser it's
just a blob of text now we can talk about some loops here I am passing in
two arrays Apple orange banana and lychee and then I'm passing another
array called N with peanut and cashew and then I'm going to create a context
and in that context I'm going to have fruits point at the list F nuts pointed
the list and list N and then zap is just the string 42 and do I even use zap in
this one no I think there's another place that it no oh yeah yeah it's I
just don't have it in the the so here's the here's the template a part of the
template it's not looking at zap and so here's the key so you we got this for
loop for X in fruits well fruits is looking up something in the context
under the key fruits their string they don't look like strings in they don't
look like strings in the template but it looks up there and it finds a list so
that little list F is what really is going on here and F is a list of apple
orange banana lychee and then X becomes the iteration variable that's only within
the template and then I'm going to print it out and then I'm going to end it so
that's like the start and end of a for loop apple orange banana lychee now
you'll notice that I have an LI tag which is the list item tag and it just
generates all that HTML and again the double curly braces are doing HTML
entity escaping automatically so so we take a look at nuts so we ask is that is
nuts present because that's a way to tell if there are if variables present
or absent if it's absent I'm going to ask another filter on the end saying how
long was it okay and so this is just this is the n nuts is the n list and it
has a length of 2 which means it has two elements in it and so we see the number
2 and so you can do various things so this is and this is an if then else the
syntax of an if then else and with curly brace curly brace percent now we can pass
objects within objects and so it's a little tricky we have a context in this
X variable and the sort of the outer key is pointing the key is outer is pointing
to another dictionary and in that dictionary there is on a key of inner
with a value of 42 and then we render the nested out HTML and you see the
outer but then outer dot inner that's so outer is is that object and then object
dot inner then this thing becomes 42 ok so you can kind of walk through objects
if you have a hierarchical objects objects that are objects that contain
objects or list that contain objects or any number of hierarchical structure of
list and objects you can walk through them so here's just another simple
example this one has data coming in instead of hard-coded so we again have
you know game 200 and we're running into game view it's a class lot view and the
200 comes in as the parameter because we said it's the parameter that comes
after the word game and so guess comes in is 200 it's a string at this point it
hasn't been converted to an integer so when Django pulls these off well it's a
it does some validation based on the types but it doesn't actually
necessarily convert them and so we're going to create a context X equals get
you know a key of guess and convert it to an integer to pass it in and then
we're going to pass the context in and the template in and so the the word guess
is going to come out and we sort of saw this the guess is 200 and then depending
on the if-then-else logic it's going to say in this case too high because your
guess was 200 and of course the right answer is always 42 so now we're going
to talk a little bit about how you manage a common text going from one
template to another through template inheritance
(jazzy piano music)