I mentioned that JavaScript owns the document object model.
The document object model is what we see
when we're looking at the browser.
A browser parses the HTML, sometimes our JavaScript
writes it and then creates this object,
we call the document object model,
which is then displayed to the user through a window.
A window is the subset of the document object model.
In whatever JavaScript we write,
we can read, manipulate, and update the DOM.
And as soon as the DOM is updated,
the user sees the updates through the window.
And we can also just go into the debugger
and directly manipulate the document object model.
So if we go back to the 01 NoScript,
there's no JavaScript in here.
So you just go, it shows you a header and a paragraph,
and that's the document object model.
But you'll note that if you go into Inspect Element
and then go into that paragraph tag,
you can change and add the word cool.
In a sense the debugger is JavaScript, right?
And you can actually type JavaScript commands
into the debugger if you do the right thing.
But the debugger is owning
the document object model as well.
And so you simply can change the document object model.
And literally, it changes the UI,
but truly the document object model changes.
So you can take a, you can even change
the kind of a tag you're dealing with.
You could turn this into an anchor tag,
you could add some hrefs.
You can change the document object model.
You're displayed, it just, you change it and you see it.
Now, I mentioned this thing called the window.
There are two sort of foundational objects
in JavaScript in the browser.
There's the DOM, and the DOM is an abstraction.
It is a structured hierarchy of tags, we call them elements.
The window is how we see it.
So you can think of this picture that I've been showing you
of parsing the response, running some JavaScript,
and tweaking the document object model
and showing it to the user.
And if you change the document object model,
it's immediately updated.
On the left, that's a kind of an oversimplification
because the way we actually view the document object model
is through the window.
The window is what's on your screen.
And probably the most easy way to demonstrate this
is to understand that the document object model
could be very large and the window could be very small.
And the document object model doesn't change
and you can resize the window back and forth.
So sometimes you see scroll bars.
The scroll bar is not a notion in the document object model,
it's a notion in the window.
The window has a certain height,
the document object model may or may not completely fit
in the window, and that has to do with the window height
and so scroll bars.
And so for example, if you look at 06height.html,
all it does is puts out the header, puts out the paragraph,
and then prints out window height and window width,
window.innerHeight and window.innerWidth.
These are the height of the window,
not the document object model,
but the window through which we're viewing it.
And so if you show this page with the debugger turned on
with a really tiny window,
it says that the height is 116.
If you make the window bigger and hit reload,
it says the height's 256.
So in JavaScript, we can ask questions about the window
and we can do things to the window.
One thing we could do is we could scroll it up and down
and that's actually a common thing to do in JavaScript.
If you have a big document object model
and you got a scroll window
and you wanna show the user a particular thing
like go to bottom,
JavaScript can scroll the window down to the bottom
or up or down, I don't get those right very well,
but we can control the window.
In this case, we're simply asking it how tall you are
and how wide you are,
but we can also control it.
And so if we take a look now and we make 07scroll.htm,
we can see that we have nine paragraphs and a header.
That is the actual content, okay?
And if we have a tall window,
we can see the whole document.
But if we make the window smaller,
then we can only see a subset of the document object model.
So the window height changes
and if you look, you now have a scroll bar
and what does the scroll bar do?
Well, it just takes and moves the document object model
up and down.
Well, it moves the part of the document object,
our view to the document object model up and down.
But if you're doing an inspect element in some browsers,
you will see that it's telling us
with little kind of annotations
that the body is being scrolled right now
and up through paragraph four is overflowed
off the screen up and paragraph seven, eight, and nine
have overflowed and they've gone off the screen below.
Now, if you play with this and you resize it
and refresh it and resize it and refresh it,
you'll see this whole, I mean, you don't,
on the left, the whole thing shows
and so body is not indicated as the scrollable element.
And the headers not overflow, et cetera.
So you can play with this,
but play with it with different sizes, refresh it,
and then inspect element and watch how the scroll,
the overflow, and the scroll bar.
And in this case, I'm not printing out height,
but you would be seeing that the height
would actually change.
So one of the things that we're gonna do next
is we're gonna modify the document object model
in JavaScript.
(upbeat music)