Now let's talk about browser events.
We've been talking about events all along.
We have done an onClick handler, which
is a shortcut to, in effect, register a click event handler,
but we're just doing it with the shortcut of the onClick
attribute.
And then when we do a setTimeout,
we're actually creating a timer event.
So the timer starts, and then when the timer expires,
the event fires, and our code is run.
So we've been doing this all along.
But there is an entire event registration system inside
the browser.
And we can say, I would like to register an event for something
to happen on this tag.
And we can hook things in all over the place.
And there's a separate event registration system.
onClick is like a shortcut using an attribute that eventually
registers the event on our behalf.
And that's why you see the little event when
you do the inspect element.
And so if we take a look at the code here,
we're going to do the same thing that we
did in 03event.htm, which we've seen before.
And then we're going to do it again in 10-event.htm.
And we're going to show the more generic way of doing it.
So in 03event.htm, we have an onClick method.
We've done this before.
And it calls my func when that method is clicked.
And if you do an inspect element,
you see that that anchor tag has an event on it.
The kind of more pure way to do it,
where we're really explicitly registering the event,
these two things are front-ends and purposes equivalent,
is we're going to, instead of having the onClick method
on the anchor tag, we're going to have an id equals zap.
And again, we have to put the id on so we can get our hands on it
inside JavaScript.
So we create an h1 and a paragraph with an anchor tag in it.
Then we start our JavaScript.
And the JavaScript starts by defining a function.
It doesn't do anything.
It just defines the function.
And then we call document.getElementByIdZap.
Now, that is grabbing that anchor tag.
And then it calls an element method called addEventListener.
And it's got two parameters.
The first parameter is I'm interested in the click event.
I want to listen for click events.
And when click events happen, call my func.
Now, again, first class functions,
there's no parentheses on my func.
That is a function reference that we defined three lines
earlier, right?
And so it accomplishes the same thing.
And if we look at 10event.htm and we take a look at it,
you see that the anchor tag with the id of zap
doesn't have an onClick on it, but it has a registered event.
And that's because we registered the event using JavaScript.
Now, if we click on it, it does the exact same thing.
That event is triggered.
It looks up and says, well, when a click happens,
I'm supposed to call my func.
And so this notion of adding event listeners
is a more general purpose notion than simply onClick.
I like to think of onClick as a shortcut to registering it.
Now, you might say it's a lot shorter.
And one thing about JavaScript is it's a bit wordy at times,
right?
document.getitementbyid.addEventListener,
a lot of JavaScript.
But it does what you need it to do.
And I'm not saying you shouldn't use onClick,
but I want to show you the more general way of doing it.
There are other kinds of events that we can connect to.
And so in this case, I'm going to just have
a header and no paragraph.
And then in my JavaScript, I'm going
to create a function.
And in that function, I'm going to log the current height
and width of the window.
When this function is called, it's only going to log it.
Now, what I'm going to say is window.addEventListener.
Now, remember, document.addEventListener,
that's a different thing, right?
Window.addEventListener is adding an event to the window.
Remember how the window is the thing
that gets larger and smaller and has scroll bars, et cetera.
So I'm saying I would like to register a bit of my code
to be called every time the window is resized.
That's what quote resized quote is.
My func is to think to call.
So now what happens is you display this,
and then you start changing the size of the window.
And on your console log, it's zoom, you know?
Window height, 135, 136, 137.
So as you're making that window larger and smaller,
your code is being called every time.
Now, why might you want to do this?
Well, one of the big things in website design
is to do what's called responsive design.
And that's as the thing gets narrower, or higher,
or smaller, like mobile.
You want to change the UI.
You might have-- on a big screen,
you might have a more complex UI.
And then on a small screen, you might
want to have a more narrow UI.
Now, often things like Bootstrap take care of all this for us.
But still, Bootstrap needs to get their hands
on the resize event so they know, whoa,
the screen size changed.
So I need to kind of tweak the markup a little bit.
So this is an example of a window event that
allows you to render an opinion as to what you want to happen
every time the screen resizes.
Now, another issue that's an important event to know about
is what's called the content load complete event.
Modern web pages are very, very complex.
I mean, the things I've been showing you
in this series of lectures are simple,
because I want you to be able to see them on a slide.
But real web pages with menus, and pretty pictures,
and colors, and spinners, all that stuff, right?
There's so many things.
You've got to download the HTML.
Then you've got a bunch of CSS, and some images,
and JavaScript libraries.
And so sometimes, you're going to just get like 100 assets
when you download a page.
The first one is the HTML.
And so the problem is, is it can take a while
for all these things to get orchestrated by the browser.
It reads the HTML.
It sees the CSS.
It loads the CSS.
It sees the JavaScript thing.
Loads the JavaScript.
It da-da-da-da.
And then it's got some images, and it takes some time.
And it does this all interleaved, and in parallel.
And eventually, you want to know, are you done yet?
Or just, are you done?
And so if we take a look at a typical page of Django
for Everybody, we see about 30 requests, and many requests.
And you'd like to know when that's all done.
Because you can't write JavaScript
that references a tag that doesn't exist yet.
Or if you want to write JavaScript
that does something to an image, like changes its size
or checks something, or hides it or shows it,
you've got to wait till the image is there before you start
messing with it, right?
So there is a special event.
It's pretty simple.
And in this, you use a script tag near the end of your body.
So we have a function, myfunk.
And in that function, the console log, the DOM is landed.
And then we're going to add event listener.
And this is a document event, because this
is DOM content loaded.
Not window, but DOM content.
Document add event listener.
The event name is DOM content loaded.
That's a hard-coded string.
And I say, please call my function
when all the files have been loaded, and we're ready.
And the user can see the page.
And so in this one, it's really short.
It's just that console, the myfunk
happens after the content is loaded,
and after all the derivative things have been loaded,
et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.