so now let's design a data model usually you start out with a user interface that
if we're going to build an application you're going to end up with a user
interface in this I'm not going to really start with a user interface I'm
going to start with like a spreadsheet view and if you've ever done something
like tried to organize your music collection with a spreadsheet or a video
collection with a spreadsheet or you know you find that spreadsheets are
super convenient because you can scroll around and do stuff and you you know
you've learned SQL you know you can go into various cells with SQL rows and
columns and update and do all the stuff but you find that after a while you you
start repeating yourself in spreadsheets and you find it's really difficult
because it's really easy when you're putting data into copy paste copy paste
paste paste paste paste and put the same stuff in but then what if you want to
change it and this is where there's a vertical replication or the replication
of data in multiple places is very bad so here's kind of an exploded table view
of that same data and the this is this it's okay this is the data that we've
got to do so if we look at the use cases of our application what we see is
there's a series of books like in this cross wisdom of crowds as a book
introduction and networking these are all books coming down here unlocking the
clubhouse so the first column is titles of books the second column is the ISBN
and then we are sort of keeping track because we're a library you know so we
might have more than one book and we're going to call those the the book
instance so instance one instance two instance three each book each physical
actual book so that you might have no physical books actually or you might
have one physical book or five physical books and each physical book might be
checked out and have a due date and so we have a status and then we have
something like say the language of the book or the genre of the book or who
wrote the book right and so that's kind of our this the data we're going to
represent in this application now when you're looking at this the first thing
you do is you go like anything where you've got vertical replication is a
problem and so you've got to be careful so you look for vertical replication and
the places that are problematic in this table view of all of our data like the
status the language the genre you see the word think think think think think those
are strings right they're not numbers okay wisdom of crowds wisdom of crowds
wisdom of crowds and the problem here with wisdom of crowds is that there are
three instances of the book but then and because we've got this all in one row I
mean one table with just a bunch of columns and not multiple tables well we
have to replicate the name wisdom of crowds three times so that we can
represent the three instances the same is true about the English language and
the genre and the author name right these are this these are these are the
same authors okay so this vertical replication is your first clue that says
that you've got to you've got to come up with a smarter data model than just this
and so the idea is is you're not allowed to put something like the string en
English in more than once in your whole database so what you have to do is you
have to split this all out somehow you have to remove duplication by making a
language table a book table and an instance table and so in the book table
you only put wisdom of crowds once and you only put the English language in
once and Spanish in once but then the problem is okay somehow we've taken this
data moved it from one big long bunch of columns to three tables with sets of
columns but we still have to represent all the original data that we were
working with before we have to represent all that stuff and so this is where we
have to be able to make connections and this is the this is the essence of
relational databases and that is they don't replicate data but they make
connections from one data item to another data item and so what we're
going to do here is in the case of the wisdom of crowds we are going to have
three book instances but somehow they all point to one book in the book table
right and so and so we have two books that point to the English language and
one points to the Spanish language now this seems like wow that wasn't such a
big deal but when you do millions of records it actually matters it's the
string data that gets you in trouble and requires far more scanning and far more
storage and another thing that happens is when you follow this rule of only one
copy well what if we wanted to turn this to uppercase EN or something that means
as long as the data is linked rather than replicated that means you're only
changing one copy okay so the replication has a performance advantage
has a storage advantage and it has a modifiability advantage when there's
only one place if we if we mistakenly misspelled the title of wisdom of crowds
it's easy we fix it it's not in these other tables whereas if we misspelled the
wisdom of crowds here we have to go find on the top one where it's just all one
big long spreadsheet we got to go and like do a search and replace but but
what if what if that's in a different column and so so that the the idea of
getting to the point where we have unique rows and we connect those rows now
I haven't told you much about how this magically works I just said we can draw
some arrows and so by drawing those arrows we got to show you how those
arrows get drawn because that's really important so this is how you start
drawing the picture of your database and so the kind of relationship we're going
to have between tables is like a many to one so when we say many to one what
we're saying is that there is one English language entry and then there
are many books that go to it so that's a many to one relationship so it could be
just one but it's many and if we look at the data model that we see from the
Django example from the Mozilla developer network we can look at this
and we can see here right this connection between the book table and
the language table has two ends to it and it has a direction to it and one end
says zero dot dot asterisk and the other end says one so this is many zero dot
dot asterisk means a number between zero and infinity including zero which means
it's possible for a book not to have a language we'd call that we call that null
in database concept so there's there's a book with no language or many books can
have one language so this is the there's one language English and there is as
many books as we want including potentially zero books right so it we
might have a language that has no books in our library with that language and
that's okay so in this one between book and language it's okay to have zero so
zero through infinity on the book side of the relationship and one on the
language side of the relationship if then we look at the the relationship
between the the book and the book instance now remember what the book
instance purpose is is to record the fact that we have multiple cop the
actual physical copies of the books that we have and so we might have multiple
copies and so if you look at this it's pretty much the same in that there is
any number of book instances from zero zero until infinities and you could have
a book in your book table for which you didn't actually own a physical copy and
that'd be okay we would know things like what its author was what its genre was
etc and then we would buy a copy of said book we'd add a copy to the instance
table and then we'd link that into that book so again you can have zero book
instances well zero through infinity book instances mapped to a single book
entry okay and so this little legend you know zero to infinity to one is is how we
read this table and you'll see database tables that have different syntaxes but
they all are capturing the same thing and that's the cardinality or the number
of things at each end of the arrow so up next we're going to show you how to
actually physically store this information in the database so far I've
been just sort of saying and there's an arrow but we have to have a way to
actually store it in the database