- Now I'm gonna talk a little bit about object life cycle and what we mean by object life
cycle is the act of creating and destroying these objects and I've been using this term
constructor already and so when we declare a variable whether it's a string or a dictionary
or a party animal whether we create them and then they're discarded and there's all this
dynamic memory that comes and goes and we as the writers of objects have the ability
to insert ourselves at the moment of object creation and at the moment of object destruction
and we make special functions that we call the constructor, the object constructor or
the class constructor and the destructor and we don't actually explicitly call them.
They're called automatically by Python on our behalf and so the constructor is much
more commonly used.
It's used to set up any initial values of variables if necessary, et cetera, et cetera.
Destructors will cover them but they're used very rarely.
So here's a bit of code that we've got.
It's our party animal and a lot of it is the same as what we've been doing so far.
So we have this variable X and the constructor has a special name, underscore underscore
init underscore.
Again we pass in the instance of the object self and in this one all we're gonna do is
print out that you're constructed and here's this code that we've had before and now we
have underscore underscore del and then we pass in self and we'll just print out that
we're being destructed and what the current value of X is for that particular instance.
So let's go ahead and run this.
This is the constructing of it and so in this case this line right here is causing the IAM
constructed message to come out.
Then we do and party, an party and that says one and two and here's an interesting thing.
We're actually gonna destroy this variable by throwing away an no longer points at that
object.
An's gonna point to 42 so we're gonna sort of overwrite an and put 42 in it and at that
point Python's like oh this whole little object that I just created somewhere it's out here.
It's vaporizing it and throwing it away and so before this line completes it actually
calls our destructor on our behalf and so that message comes out.
So we are allowed as the builder of these objects to add these little chunks of code
that says I want to be involved at the moment this object is created and I want to be involved
at the moment that this object is destroyed.
Now in this last line an is no longer a party animal, an is now an integer.
It's got a 42 in it, it's gone, it's been created, it was used and then it was destroyed.
So you gotta be careful if you overwrite something you can sort of throw the object away.
So the constructor is a special block of code that's called when the object is created to
set the object up.
So we can create lots of instances, everything we've done so far is we make a class and then
we create one instance, one object and each of these objects end up being stored in its
own variable.
We have a variable an and we've been using it but the more interesting thing begins to
happen when we have multiple instances of the same class sitting in different variables
and it has its own copy of the instance variables.
So let's take a look at this.
So this code here I've taken out the destructor and it shows a little bit more information.
So now we're gonna put two variables in here, we're gonna have a current score or whatever
and a name.
And this time we're going to add a parameter onto the constructor and so the self comes
in sort of automatically as the object is being constructed but if we put a parameter
on the constructor call which is this party animal call then this comes in as the z variable.
And so self is the object itself and z, this first parameter, is whatever parameter we
put here.
Everything we've done so far has no parameter here but now we have a parameter here.
And then that means that when we call this constructor name is gonna be Sally in this
particular thing and then it'll say oh self.name which will be Sally who's been constructed.
And so then we have this and that object is now constructed and then we put it in the
variable s and then we call the party method on that and we construct a different one.
And so this time it calls and z is Jim and we basically have another copy of this.
As it runs down here when this is called it makes one instance and stores that in the
variable s.
And there's a variable x in there, there's a name in there, there's an init method in
party and that's all in here.
All that stuff is in here.
And now we say let's make and that's gonna have Sally in there on s party then this turns
into a one.
Then we're gonna do another constructor and so it's gonna make a whole new thing and it's
gonna store that in j and this one's gonna have Jim in it.
And then we're gonna call j party, that turns that into a one and then s party will cause
this to be a two.
So what happens is we have now two objects, one in the variable s and one in the variable
j and they have separate copies of their instance variables.
These are the instance variables or the object fields or whatever, but they're the variables.
But the key is that every time we do a new construction it duplicates this and there's
another copy of it.
So there's an x within s, so s.x is this variable and j.x is that variable, okay.
So the next thing we'll talk about is inheritance and that's the idea of taking one class and
extending it to make something new.
(jazz piano music)