So now I want to show you another example of many-to-many
from an application that's near and dear to my heart
and that's the autograder that I use
for most of my online classes.
So one of the things the autograder has to know
is like who is in what course
so that we can track grades based on people and courses.
And so this is the data model
and it's a little bit different syntax.
You sort of see one-to-many.
It's using what's called crow's feet
and you see this little crow foot
and that's like a many when it sort of spreads out
and then you sort of have this one
and there's various little ways
and one or more or zero or more
and so there's little, it's called a crow's foot diagram.
But these diagrams ultimately are capturing the same thing
whether these relationships are many-to-many
or one-to-many and what the cardinality
of each end of the relationship is.
And this is showing a person table,
a course table and a membership table
and this is a very common thing that we have to solve
in educational systems and it's a little bit
more sophisticated than the previous one
which I thought was beautifully elegant and simple
but I wanna show you this one as well.
And so what we have here is basically
a people are in courses, right?
A person can be in many courses
and a course can have many people
so it's a many-to-many relationship.
We create a through table.
We'll call it a member table.
We end up just like before with two one-to-many's pointing out
or many-to-ones pointing outwards
so we have a person ID and a course ID in the member table.
All three of these tables have primary keys
of ID, ID and ID and then we put the little tiny
sort of virtual set in here so that at a person
you can just look at a virtual set of their courses
and of course you can say who are the members of this course.
Now we're gonna do one more thing
that's a little bit different here
and that is often the simplest of through tables
is literally an ID and two foreign keys.
And as a matter of fact, some people,
Django doesn't like doing this
but some people don't even include the ID field
and they just make the combination
of the two foreign keys as a unique ID inside.
And if you're doing databases directly
you can actually do that.
But here's a thing that you can also do.
So if you think about in a teaching and learning situation
people aren't just members of courses.
They are members of courses and they have a role
and is that role as a learner, a teaching assistant
or an instructor or perhaps
they're the departmental administrator, right?
And that is an attribute of the connection, right?
The connection between a person and a course
is the membership and oh by the way
they're not just a member,
they're a member with some metadata, okay?
And so sometimes we add data to the through table
and it's actually quite useful
and it's really the only place to model this kind of data
because somebody might be in a course as a teacher
and they might be in a different course as a student
so you can't just say this person is always a teacher
or they're always a student, you can't say that.
It depends on the context and so that's why
at the connection between a particular person
and a particular course we actually model
the role that they have in that course.
So here we go.
So we're going to have a person in a course
and we're going to have a through table, a membership
and so we're gonna send these things
back and forth to each other
and this membership is the tricky one
and so we have a foreign key over to person
and a foreign key over to course
and we're gonna model some information.
We're gonna model a created date at
and this is a date time field, this is another feature
that basically says let's make a created underscore at
and dear Django, I'm not even gonna set this value.
Please, when I create this, a new record here,
populate this at the current date and time
and if I make a change to it, change the updated at
and this is a common pattern in lots of tables
to put these two lines in and it's so common
that we often call them the same field.
So you'll look in somebody's Django model
and you'll see created at and you'll see updated at
and so that's another thing we're modeling
at the connection in the through table
and so the other thing we're going to do is have the role.
Now the example that you use in local library,
they make this role I think a string
which makes me kind of like feel bad
'cause I don't like vertical replication of string
even if they're sort of from a fixed vocabulary.
So what we're gonna do here is we're gonna do something
where we're going to create a set of integers
and associate those integers with meaning
and use them in the admin interface, et cetera
and so what I'm gonna do here is these learner IA, GSI,
instructor and admin are just integer numbers
and then I'm going to say I'm gonna make
this little tuple of tuples or a list of tuples as it were
and the learner integer maps to the string learner
so we can show that in the user interface.
This here is a lot of UI stuff so in the admin UI,
this whole member choices thing affects the admin UI.
When this is all said and done,
we basically say the role is an integer field
and I like that because it's short and I love integers.
How many times have you heard me say I love integers?
Integers are short and efficient
and instead of just being any number,
it really is the choices are pulled from this thing
which is these possible numbers
which is one, 1,000, 2,000, 5,000 or 10,000
and the default value is learner which means it's a one.
So this is a nice, this is basically not,
you could make an integer field and we could code
in our Python code these numbers and these strings
but there's a lot of value in using
the administrator interface now
and having these values known inside the data model
rather than just coding them throughout
all the Python code that we write.
So when this is all said and done,
what we have is two foreign keys,
two outbound foreign keys like you would expect,
a created and updated app that's totally maintained
by Django for us and then modeled at the connection
a role like are you a teacher, are you a student?
Okay, and so that's a little more sophisticated
kind of many-to-many model and we can talk to this
in the Django shell, Python 3, many manage.py shell.
You know, we import the models from the application models
that this is really reading the models.py file
from the many folder, import the person model,
the course model, membership, those are Python classes.
We're gonna make a person and save it.
We're gonna make a course and save it.
We can check the ID to prove that.
We can look at all of the members values,
that's a query set and then with nothing in it
and then we can create a membership
and we give membership.instructor,
this is that number, right?
I think that was like 1,000 or 5,000 I think what that was
and then courses_c, whoops, how come it's not around?
There we go, courses_c in person is p,
that's taking from the p and c variable that we just created.
We are basically populating the true table
with the two objects from which we'll figure out
what that foreign key is and then we save it.
We can see that it's been saved by looking at ID
and so we can see these things like c members values now.
We can see that this is the person
who is a member of that particular course
and we can see what courses Ted is in
and Ted's in Woodcraft.
And so this is just another example using the shell
to talk to some many-to-many relations.
So up next we're gonna show
how we do these shell-like operations
but we're actually gonna just write Python code
rather than typing Python code.
(upbeat music)