Hello and welcome to another code walkthrough on Django for everybody.
We're gonna walk through some sample code today.
It's the CIF code that really starts using the many-to-many work a bit.
And it's our forums code, okay?
So let's just walk through how it works.
The idea, I've got two users logged in here, just two different users.
This is also gonna demonstrate the owner pattern again.
So let's add a forum, forum, forum one, hello.
So this is just crud at this point.
And so this looks like most of the crud things that we've built.
I won't go through and delete because the interesting part is here in the detail page.
And so I can put a comment in, this is person, this is Firefox comment.
So I've got one user logged in on Firefox, submit.
And then I will refresh here in the other one and I see forum one.
So let me just make a comment, and this is Safari.
So you can see that this is the Firefox comment and the Safari comment.
And now if I hit refresh here in forum three, you can see the Safari comment and the Firefox
comment, which I didn't even get my typographical error done right.
Well, the key is now you see the delete button is appropriate.
So the comments are owned.
And what's even more important is sorry about that typo is there's multiple of them, right?
So now if I just hit refresh here, you can see that and see these things happening.
So there's, so for one forum, each user can have many comments, right?
And so this has to be a many to many relationship.
So and then if I go back to all forums, this guy sees the edit and the delete, and then
this one does not see the edit and delete.
So you get the idea that that's pretty much what it does.
So let's take a look at the code here.
There is not too much tricky in the urls.py, most of the urls.py is like all crud things
we've built, but the comment is yet another table because there's really two tables here.
There's the forum table and the comment table.
And so we've done stuff like this where we've got two tables involved.
There's actually three tables involved, but one of them is the user.
So we'll come back to this a little bit.
There's not too much outrageous or new in that, but we do have two models.
So let's get that back on.
The first model is the forum model.
And this is other than this new many to many field, this is really very straightforward.
It looks like almost everything we've been doing that's crud, it's got some fields and
it's got an owner key.
And so again, there is a table out there.
There is a model out there, the user model that's out there.
And we're in effect drawing a picture.
This is a one to many, so that oops, let's draw this, pen working, and come on pen, there
we go.
So owner is a one to many relationship, that is that there is a user table and then there
is a forum table and each user can have many forums.
So each user can have many forums, so that is our table.
Now what's going to happen is the interesting part is here, but let's first talk about the
comment table.
So the comment table is down here and the comment table has one user can have many comments
and one forum can have many comments as well.
And so because in a sense there is a, let me change color here, come on change color,
let's go violet, because there is a many to many relationship between users and forums
with a little bit of comment data sitting right there in the middle, we have to model
it as, that has to be modeled as a completely separate table.
So there's only two tables here, but really there's three tables here because the user
table is participating in both of these models.
And so we'll come back to the many to many field.
So this is the comment and like connection tables or junction tables or join tables it
has two foreign keys, it's the most important thing, it's the keys in each direction, I
guess I shouldn't change that right, so we got the user table, we got the comment table
and we got the forum table.
So forums can have many comments, users can have many comments, these are forum and so
a user can have many forums.
So this side of it is a foreign key and this is a foreign key as well, right, coming out
of the comment table there are two foreign keys and look at that, there's a forum key
aimed at the forum model and then a foreign key coming out of the comment to the user
model.
Now again we've talked about in the lectures, we've talked about modeling data at the connection,
so the text that we're getting is the text, the text that we're getting at the modeling
point is this text right here, it is the actual comment itself and you could make a different
table for it but it's just as easy to model it right in the middle of the junction field,
okay and so that's pretty much it and we have to in the forums field we are basically saying
look we're going all the way through the comment model and we're coming out the other end in
the user model.
This related name is really really important and that's basically a name, let me draw my
picture again, I should have probably just drawn this picture and kept it, the user table,
the forum table and the comment table, forum has many comments, user has many comments,
and so in a sense what we're seeing here is this basically says that there is a relationship
dot dot dot dot dot dot dot dot between forums and users and it is in the comments table,
the table that it goes through is the comments table, that's what the through means and then
the related name equals forum comments is actually you're installing in the user object
a method, an attribute, something in this user model that says forum comments so we're
actually extending the user model, if we were looking at the user we could say hey what
are the forum comments for this user and that would give us a, it would come over here and
it would come over here and give us a list of all the comments, but this related name
is the name of this attribute and you don't necessarily need all the time to be able to
do this but the problem is after a while when you're plugging so many things into the user
model you can end up with name conflicts and so it's good to name this thing even though
we might not use it so I hope that, hope that helps so this is a pretty straightforward
thing other than the fact that the user model is our third table and we're using it in both
places so there is that.
So the forms, so the only place I'm using a form in here is this comment form so I just
made it and the reason that I made a comment form is that I wanted to be able to make it
look pretty, I wanted to be able to use crispy and so instead of just making this comment
form on the detail page out of HTML I just made a form so I could use crispy in the detail
page.
So that's the forms, the views are pretty straightforward, the create, the delete, we'll
come back to comment create and comment delete, they're not all that tricky either, probably
the trickiest thing going on in here is the forum detail view and we're extending owner
detail view and the template name and the model and all that stuff and we're not, we're
not going to post actually, you'll see in a second, we're not going to post back to
this so we only need to get and so if you look at owner detail view, I guess I should
open up another tab, this is dot dot my hearts owner, owner detail view extends detail view
which basically demands a primary key and so there is this primary key value, don't
do that, don't do that, undo, there is this primary key value that's going to come in
and that's going to come in from the detail view which is the second parameter which is
forums, forum three, so we're going to go grab and load that object, I could have made
that a getter 404, I probably actually should have made that a getter 404, so that's going
to load the forum object and the forum object is the title and the text and the owner of
the forum itself but then what I'm going to do is I'm going to say go get me all of the
comment objects filtered so that the forum value in the model equals the current forum,
this forum, that is the forum we just loaded, that's the forum key in the model so the first
one is this forum in models and the second one is this variable, I could have, I could
have changed this to be, I'm not going to change it but I could have changed this to
be x, I could have changed this to be x, I'm not going to save it, although it might be,
maybe I'll just save it, make sure I've got all of comment forum, forum, forum, let's
just make this be x too because that's the variable, I hope I don't break the code by
doing this, I'm trying to show you that this is a field in the model and this is just a
variable in this view, right, okay, so this is going to give us a list of comments, in
a sense this is kind of like a list view, if you're dealing with a list view you've
got to write a for loop to go through it in the thing so we got all the comments for this
thing and we're passing in the comment forum, that's simply constructing it, it's constructing
this comment forum and then we're going to basically render the request, so we'll close
that one and so let's take a look at this detail page, this detail page is what generates
this forum, a lot of it's pretty much the same, check to see if you're the owner before
you put up the little button, little pencils, that's quite nice, print out the forum title,
print out the forum text, print out, this stuff is all the forum title, text and how
long ago it, with the natural time, so that's pretty straightforward, so that's really not
all that tricky, so then what we're going to do here is if the user is logged in, and
so it turns out that this does not require login and so the only time we're going to
show this comment form is if the user is logged in, so this part right here is if the user
is logged in, be our clear equals all is what stops, brings this stuff back to the left
margin even though I floated these things over using CSS, load the crispy form tags
and then I'm going to build the form, that's this comment form that goes from the word
comment, the word text, the submit button and the all forms which is just an on-click
JavaScript that sends us back to the all forms page and that is the end of the user authenticated
because it turns out that seeing all this stuff, seeing the actual comments, that's
okay, non-login users can see it and then if you recall, going back to the views, we
sent in the comments and the comments is a list of comments ordered by, in descending
order, most recent first and I guess you don't see it there but they are most recent first
but at that point we are just going to write a for loop to loop through all the comments,
print out the comment text, print out the comment updated at and if the owner of the
comment is the current logged in user, put out a little trash icon, put out a little
trash icon.
So that generates the output, that generates this page but let's take a look at a couple
of things that we're going to do.
So you see this, this first two things, right, we are actually going to post with action
equals this form right here, the comment form, blah, does not post back to forums detail
page.
This is the forums detail page.
If you look at it, it points to posts, forum, comment, create.
So let's go back to that, forum, comment, create is right here and so it's just going
to run this comment, create view, passing in the primary key of the forum, okay.
So then if I go into my views, forum, create, no, comment, create view.
So comment, create view is what's going to happen when I get this post, right.
So the post is going to come in, there's going to be a comment field which is this text field
and there is the primary key of the forum, not the comment.
So now we are going to make the connection.
This is where we're actually making the connection and you'll notice that I'm just saying login
required view in view because I don't have an automated way to do this and so I'm going
to do it by hand.
So we're in the post, we're going to go grab the forum object by applying primary key,
there I am using a getter 404 so at least I blow up in the right way.
Then what I'm going to do is I am going to, let's go back to models, I've got to fill
out the text field, the forum field and the owner field and the owner field are the two
foreign keys and come back, come back, come back, in the many to many we have to have
those objects available to us.
So we are going to build a new comment, this doesn't store it in the database, the text
field comes from the request post, the owner field is current request user and the forum
field, the foreign key in this middle connector table is this forum object that we just loaded.
So that fully populates a comment object, it fully populates a comment object in that
post method and then all we have to do is we have to say save it.
So the comment.save takes that in memory comment that we created with the two foreign keys
in the comment and sticks it in the database.
And then all we have to do is redirect.
Now what we want to redirect back to is we want to redirect back to this detail page
because we don't want to redirect back to ourselves and we don't want to redirect back
to all forums and so we have, when we hit submit we want to come back here so it just
looks like that thing showed up but really it was a full request response cycle where
it posted to comment create view but after the post was done it did a redirect and we're
doing a post redirect so it's cool anyways.
And so this is a slightly different version of the reverse.
It is the same concept as what we've seen all along where we have like a forum ID inside
a second parameter to the URL because the reverse in this URL thing, I wish they'd call
this reverse because that's what it's doing the URL is just kind of a wrapper for reverse.
Well this is the two parameter form.
So we have a one parameter form of URL which is this one which says go URL forums colon
all, says give me the URL to the view that is named all within forums.
Here I'm saying URL forums forum create forum ID.
This is saying this one needs a primary key because if you go into urls.py the forum create
demands a parameter and so we're feeding it but you can also feed that in in a reverse
and you do it with this funky format.
I wish that was by position but no it's not.
You have this args keyword and it's sending in a list of variables and the variable is
the primary key which is the number which is this three.
So redirecting to forum slash forum slash three and that's where the three comes from.
Okay.
So the only thing to look at next is what happens when I hit the delete button.
So let's take a look at the detail page.
So remember that we cannot delete in a get but we have to delete in a post.
So in here I am not, this is the trash can.
The trash can is not going to do the deleting.
The trash can is going to link to forums comment delete with comment ID.
So there's this number three but each of these comments has a comment ID.
So let's just inspect this is you can see in the bottom it's comment seven.
This one is comment four.
So that is the comment ID because we're looping in this code we are looping through for comment
and comments so each comment has the primary key.
So with all that I am just going to click on it and of course we're going to have a
verification page that turns the get into a post in a sense.
I mean it's just a page and so we've gone to comment delete view so forums comment seven
delete and if you look at the urls.py forums comment seven delete and we give it a name
and we're going to rope through to comment delete view so if we take a look at our comment
delete view well what's pretty cool is that we can mostly use owner delete view because
by now we know it the object we know that we're in the comment model the template we're
going to work with is comment delete which is pretty straightforward.
So it's going to go find and so you'll notice we don't have a get in here we don't have
a post in here and that's because we're inheriting all that from owner delete view you the owner
delete view now the only thing we're overriding is the get of the success url because the
success url when we're all done we want to go back to the forum not seven but three see
how we're going to go back to form three and it looks like that just went away and so the
success url is actually needs to be computed based on the current forum and so we are overriding
the get success url which is part not exactly of owner delete view but the models the generic
delete view we are returning a string and if you go and you read self.object.forum self.object
points to the current comment so if this is we're in the middle of comment for delete
while we're running in this view self.object is the comment right that's number four comment
number four but comment number four.forum is the primary key of the forum that this
object belonged to by the time oops by the time we're here getting the success url it's
actually been deleted but we still have a in memory copy of it so we're going to go
to the forums I do not intend dragging it by mistake trying to highlight it right so
it's been deleted but we have it sitting here in the memory and so we can get its former
primary key but we can get the forums primary key object doesn't exist in the database anymore
but the memory copy does and so we know what that number is so then we go to this fancy
reverse again with a parameter and so that's how we get back let's see what happens in
the cancel cancel cancel oh so it's the cancel right so the cancel does this the cancel generates
the url forum detail with a comment which is the current object and then a foreign key
into forum and the primary key of the forum so comment forum id is what generates this
url and there is that url it goes back to the forum detail page so if i go cancel it
goes back to the right page and that's because comment you can walk you're walking the foreign
key in this particular situation so i think that we pretty much have covered everything
just check the views yeah we've covered pretty much everything that's unique in this particular
bit of code and again the new part here is to have a connector model and then have a
many-to-many field the rest of this is very much similar to many of the other things that
we have talked about so i hope this has been helpful to you and now you can start playing
with many-to-many kinds of connections cheers