- Hello and welcome to our lecture on owned rows in Django.
So what do I mean by an owned row?
Well up to now, every CRUD application that you've written,
you got a table or a model or two, maybe they're connected,
but basically if you log in, you can edit every row.
And so if you do a list, you see an update
and delete button on every row.
Real applications don't work that way.
If you're building a classified ad system,
some ads belong to you and some ads belong to other people,
you can see them all, but you can't edit them all.
And so we have to decide when to put the edit
and delete buttons up and only do those for the owner.
And we gotta make it so you can't like sneak in
and edit and delete other people's stuff.
And so we have to protect these rows
from being edited or deleted by anybody but the owner,
but anybody can see them.
And so that's why I call them owned rows.
If there's a row that you own,
you will see an edit or delete button.
If there's a row you don't own,
you'll see the row and the data
and you'll be able to read it and view it and that's it.
And so if we go back to how we were working
in our CRUD application, we were making heavy uses
of these generic views, the generic list view.
And so when we're all said and done
after a whole bunch of machinations,
you ended up with a very, very simple view.
You ended up with a horse list view
that extended generic list view.
Generic list view is provided to us by Django.
And the only thing we had to do was take this code,
which is several thousand lines of code,
and inform it as to which model we want it to be
and then we make another view, right?
So we make the horse list view
by extending generic list view
and informing that list view
that we wanna do this in the model with horses.
And from that point on, all kinds of convention happens.
And so we know things like
the variable will be named horse list.
It'll be a list of objects that are retrieved from,
a list of model objects that are retrieved from the database.
And so we kinda know how that works.
And it makes things really simple, not a lot of repetition.
Every view kinda looks the same.
You probably have done cats or dogs or autos,
a couple of different things.
And they all look very much the same
and if you get good at it,
you should be able to make these changes very rapidly.
So if we look at how this is working
kinda from an object oriented perspective,
we are making a new class called gView.Views.HorseListView
and we are extending our parent class
is the generic list view
and we're sort of adding our own little special sauce
by saying one class variable, model equals horse.
Okay, so that's kinda what's going on here.
Now, in this owner view,
we're going to do something quite similar.
And that is when we're going to have an article
and this is all from the DJ Free Samples My Arts example,
we're going to extend owner list view.
Now if we were, and soon we will look inside owner list view
and we will see that owner list view
is extending generic list view
and where this model equals article
is informing owner list view,
the difference is this is our code.
That belongs to us and in the last part,
we will show you everything that you have to do
to build one of these things.
And so we're taking the list view
which has almost everything we want
and we're gonna add one feature to it
and then we're gonna extend the list view
and create a new view called owner list view
or you might call it list view for owned rows.
And at that point, you're good
and this has this class owner list view
which we'll see in a second,
has everything you need to deal with rows that are owned.
And for example, we're going to have a owner column.
So every article is gonna have an owner
and if that's equal to the current logged in user,
then we're going to show these little edit and delete buttons.
But if the article owner,
the owner value inside the article object or the model,
if that owner is not equal to the current user,
we don't show it.
Now, not showing a link does not mean
you've protected it from editing.
We'll show you later how that protection from editing happens.
But this is such a common problem
that we wanna just be able to, in a sense,
say look, here's a list view.
Here's a list view with this special owner column in it
and we wanna maintain the owner column.
We don't wanna have to write hundreds of lines of code
in every view that we wanna have this owner column.
So we just use object-oriented techniques to accomplish this.
And so we're going to use inheritance
and we talked about it and we'll talk about it again.
Inheritance is the idea that you have a class,
you're gonna make another class that inherits all of its,
all that parent class and then extends it,
adds a little bit of stuff to it.
And it's another form of don't repeat yourself.
Do something once in a parent class.
You make the parent class sometimes quite generic.
Then you make a child class that extends the parent class
and then we use the child class.
Or we could call them subclasses or child classes.
There's a whole bunch of different terminology
and it's all pretty much equivalent.
Subclasses are more specialized versions of a class.
They inherit attributes and methods
from their parent classes and can introduce their own.
Again, basic object-oriented programming.
So up next we're gonna talk a little bit
about how it is that we can peek in
to one of these generic views
and add our own special sauce for it.
(jazz music)