so up to now we've mostly just talked about how forms work we've been talking
about how forms work across whatever programming language you're using or
framework you're using we've mostly talked about how the browsers treat forms
how we generate HTML to make forms how posts work how refresh works how post
redirect works how CSRF works that's other than subtle details those are
topics that are true no matter what you do no matter what what language you're
writing in or what framework that you're using now we're gonna pivot a little bit
and talk about how Django helps you do all those things that we just got done
talking about doing so if you look at this picture if you look at the picture
you see that like forms are kind of in the middle of this picture that's the
final piece we're filling in and forms are connected a lot of ways forms can be
connected to models they're used in the view and they're used in templates and
so they're a very powerful part and all the things we've been doing is
abstractions where we write a little bit of code and find lots of ways to reuse
that code or we write some code that extends an object and then we add a
little bit to it and then we've got some very powerful object when we're all said
and done and so that's what we're doing here in forms and forms can be used in
views they can be using templates and they can interact even with models and
so it's we're gonna talk a lot about forms there's a lot of like just menial
labor that just work and informs and if you really had to build all the HTML by
from scratch like I did in some of those earlier examples it's just really
painful and there's other problems too and that is that you know there's just a
lot of repeating yourself we kind of avoid one will use like object-oriented
techniques and other techniques to not repeat ourselves and it and it it's
really easy to put a HTML for a crappy form but why why wouldn't you want a
beautiful form and so if you write the HTML and you write some CSS and you do
kind of crappy version of it then you have to fix it or hand it to a designer
and then they have to go fix 100 pages there are things in Django crispy forms
is something we'll talk about later that just like says hey I'm using forms in
Django wait a second I want them to be pretty now and then you just make them
pretty and if you want to change how they're pretty you can change how that
works and then you change them all at the same time and so not repeating
yourself being able to like lean on utility code seems like why would we do
this but in complex applications you just fall in love with this idea that
that you don't have to repeat yourself and even though I showed you some of the
things like post redirect refresh CSRF all that stuff it's even more complex
than that especially when you start talking about pulling data from the
database and putting it in an edit form and then checking to see if the data is
valid if the data is not valid send back an error form give a chance to resubmit
it if they're successful you do post redirect and then you send a message in
the session we've done all that in really simple but if you really look at
everything that you need to look at it's pretty complex and so we're not going to
do all this in this first lecture but this gives you a sense of the kinds of
things that a create form where you're gonna go like you know new cat and then
you got some forms to fill out fields to fill out about the cat and then you hit
the save and so if we just go through this these are the steps you need to do
to insert a cat in your cat database right so your browser initially goes and
gets a get request and then you you fill out the empty form with a bunch of fill
in the blank fields the user can almost cancel out of that and get out the user
might enter some data and hit post now the problem is what if you have some
rules about the data such as this is required that has to be at least five
characters etc you have to then send an a form back with that data to let them
fix it and resubmit it again or if it's good you go ahead and store the data in
the database but then we have to put some kind of a success message like in a
session or something and then send a redirect out and then the browser
immediately comes back and gets the redirect URL which pulls the message out
sends the page and sends the success and so we've done parts of this already
right we've done parts of this already the big part we haven't done is kind of
like this middle part here where we're like validating the data and have this
error retry loop that we put the user back in the loop and give them another
chance now that's the create form the edit process where you're pulling in an
existing cat and you're going to edit their fields is even more complex you
know you you'll go load up a cat but you might have an error page because you
don't get the you don't get the unit they're looking for a cat that didn't
exist under database you send out the form with the old data they might leave
they might edit it they might come back they might validate the data and get an
error then they have to fix the data they got to go around here until okay we
got some valid data and then you store the data in the database send out a put
a message in a session send out a redirect to a success URL and that
success URL you put out the message in and say yay so that's that's complex too
and and we're going to figure that out delete is not as simple as you might
see in the problem with deleting things is that you can't delete with a get
request so usually you have to go navigate it like you see a little delete
button you click on it you go to a delete page it's going to load the data
that you'll want to delete so you can build a confirmation page confirmation
pages turn out to be really important because they're also our tricky way to
convert a get to a post but if they're asking for the wrong data we have to
send an error message otherwise we send a conversion for confirmation form that
says are you sure you want to delete this that's both nice for the user to
give a confirmation but it also then turns this into a form and of course they
can leave with a cancel but if they click on yes that turns into a post and
it has the key so the first thing it does is it has to load the data again
from the model and then if that data is not there they got the wrong key then
you send an error page out and if you got the right key and they have the
user has permission to delete the data then you go talk to the model and you
delete the thing right then you put a congratulations on your deletion in a
session or something then go with a redirect because you can't respond with
a 200 you got to respond with a 302 and then the browser immediately does it get
a success URL pulls the message out of session makes a success page with the
message now we're going to cover this a bunch of times so you don't have to get
this the first time but I just am telling you that forms are complex and
what's cool is Django form objects that we're going to create act like glue they
can generate the HTML they allow for a consistent look and feel and they allow
for you to change the look and feel when the post data comes back from the
browser in a form that it created then it puts it all in the right spot it
validates the data based on a set of rules that you say like this has to be
this kind of a thing and that kind of a thing or a date or a character or an
integer or a floating point whatever it is the rules are that's all done for you
in Django and if something goes wrong then it hands you an error form that you
can send right back to the user and really greatly and then of course once
it's validated it moves it into a model and then actually can even to the
database store automatically so the form is like this blue thing that sort of
talks to templates it talks to browsers it reads data from browsers it's like
stuff and and so in a way that the form is like the controller it's like the
view it's it just makes your views really succinct and you're gonna you're
gonna love it once you understand it so here is a simple form and so forms live
in a file called forms.py not surprisingly and basically just like
them it looks a lot like the models file and so you're gonna see that the one
thing that forms do differently is they can have these things called validators
models have rules about max length etc but there are even more complex
validators and you can even write code that you have your own functions that be
when the form is coming in you're gonna look at this one field that you're gonna
say like oh I wanted two uppercase characters followed by three lowercase
characters sorry you didn't do what I said that's what's called a validator
and that's when that error page goes back and it says hey you're missing this
stuff and we'll show you how the validator stuff works but basically you
put in little lines just like you did for the model and you're effectively
defining a user interface plus a bunch of logic behind it now the one thing I'm
not doing in this particular section will do soon is connecting this to a
model so you could say wait a sec I'd like to make a form and I will really
mostly want to inherit from a model you can do that but that's not this one
that's coming up in the whole next section but it won't be long so the form
object right we're gonna so here's this form we just made it's got three fields
in it and this is a real simple view it's not useful it just kind of shows
you one of the things you can do so make a basic form when the basic form is
defined as having these three fields and then you say form and then call the
method as table and so what this produces it's just a dump there's
nothing the UI this looks really ugly but basically it generates all this HTML
for you all this HTML input tags and it's we told it to do it as table that's
necessarily not necessarily prettiest way to do it but all that HTML is
generated from the form utility so it can send it out as a list you can set it
out as paragraphs etc etc etc and so this is just to show you kind of the
dump if you go to this URL do a view source on it so you see this stuff in
here so that you define a form object and one of the things you can do is make
me HTML and this is not a good example we'll come up in a bit with a better
example the better example of course is to use it in a template and so here is a
template with a simple form in it we got a form it's a post we got some submit
stuff we got ourselves a cancel you know button that we put in and we got a
CSRF token and we're going to use that form as table and we're going to
surround it by a table tag so that it looks a lot prettier and so this is a
far more typical way of doing it that first one was just to dump it and so
this when you do this and you give it you you sort of make the form in a get
get request you make the form and you pass it into the context if you
remember form dot as table that's a very come back too far too far form dot as
table came from the context came from the passed in variable and that is right
here and right here and so we make the form object which has all the fields in
it and then we pass it into our view our template and it renders that and so then
this is what it looks like much prettier and if you do a view source of that if
you go to this form create and you do a view source on that you'll see it's all
that same table stuff you know it's the same table stuff that we had before it's
just now wrapped in some stuff to make it look a little prettier we put a submit
button it's got a form tag and then you can actually hit the submit button and
something actually happens so this is by far the more typical way of using the
form in a template so I talked about the create form the update form and the
delete form this is kind of an example of how forms can be used now I'm not
actually talking in the model yet we'll do that in a bit so I'm just going to
pretend that we have some old data and so this normally would come from the
model this old data title mileage purchase date that would come from the
model normally but for now we're just gonna like make it up and so then you
basically start a form and you pass this old data in and as the constructor
that's a constructor for a basic form from the basic form class pass in old
data and give me back the form up give me back an object of basic form of type
basic form and I'm going to have it in the variable form and then I'm going to
pass it into context now you'll notice I'm using the exact same template the
one I showed you before because that form as table understands that sometimes
there's data in these fields and it properly puts the data in it properly
escapes the data it understands that this is a number it understands that
this is a date it's got all that stuff all figured out right and so this is how
it works as you just somehow get your hands on key value pairs of the old
data you pass it into the constructor and now you render the form and the forms
library takes care of putting in all that old data believe you me you're
probably glad I'm not showing you how to do you know HTML and code and all these
things and when you do encode but this is a little different because it's
inside of an attribute you don't want to know that because you just are going to
use format table and it's got all the rules figured out and this is hundreds
of lines of code that you're not writing so next we're going to talk about the
validation part so that's actually what happens when we receive data back from
the browser