So now we're gonna talk about data validation.
Data validation is what happens when you hit the Submit button
and then that data is sent to the server.
And what the server does is it checks that post data
that it's getting to see if it's proper according to its rules.
So if you go back to this picture I showed you
in the create form, the part we're talking about now
is really this part right here.
Where the user has entered their data,
they've hit the Submit button,
and we in the server are going to look at that data.
And then we are going to decide if it's an error,
send back a form, or store the data.
And we're actually sort of just have a comment
say store the data, and then go to the success.
So we're really looking at this part right here
of receiving and validating the data
and then taking all those actions, okay?
So the idea of data errors is you're typing in a form
and you forget your zip code.
And you hit the button and a little red box pops up
and says, "Zip code is required."
Now you can also tell the fields in the browser
that they're required so that the browser
won't even send the data.
That's different and not all browsers do that.
So you still have to check if you really want the zip code.
You've got to check to make sure the zip code is there.
Now in this one I made it just to generate errors.
I made a validator on that form, if you recall,
that said that all the titles have to be
at least two characters.
And here's a little message.
Please enter two or more characters if that's not true.
'Cause otherwise the fact that it's not a string
or a number or whatever because the browser
is a little too smart for us.
So I had to come up with a validator
that would fail in the server and not fail in the browser.
You still need to validate data in the server.
So you type some stuff in.
You make a mistake, like in this case,
the title was only one letter.
I hit the submit button and now what I want to see
isn't a thing that tells me what the errors are
and gives me a chance to fix it,
including putting the old data that I just posted, right?
So it gives me my post data back.
And then I get a chance to resubmit.
So again, here's the data form.
And the validator there, it's a min length validator.
If you go look at the documentation,
there's a jillion validators.
This was really simple and it fits on a slide.
So basically, in addition to whatever,
the fact that it's gotta be a character field,
I want it to be at least two characters.
And that's not a crazy validator to have
because you might have a post that says,
look, you're not gonna have a title of one character
when you're doing a blog post or something like that, right?
You might say, look, at least five characters.
So now we're gonna walk through that process.
And so if you take a look at this code from the form,
in comes a get request.
And that get request is gonna show up with some old data.
It's going to create the form with the initial settings.
It's gonna build a context
that it's gonna pass into the render.
Same render form that just makes the thing
with the table tags and CSRF and form post.
And so at this point, we are a get request.
We are returning a 200,
which is returning the HTML for that page, right?
So that's the first part of it.
And that is in the edit process,
get the old data, show it to the user
and give the user an opportunity to change the data.
So now we change the data, right?
And let's just say we didn't make any mistakes.
You changed a few numbers, you hit the post,
which gathers up all this stuff
and sends it as a post request to the server.
So then what happens is it comes into the post method.
See how these class based views are so dang pretty, right?
So pretty.
And so request post, right?
All that data coming from the form comes into request post.
And you just construct the basic form and say,
hey, basic form, your old data is from the post.
And all the fields are named the right way
and the key value pairs.
I mean, this is basically a dictionary,
but the form made the key value pairs.
It knew what names to name all the forms.
So it named them.
And so it's not surprising.
It knows exactly what to expect in there, right?
And so it takes a look at the post data
and then it constructs us a form object, right?
It constructs us a form object
and basically says if there was a validation failure,
if not form is valid, then we're gonna do one thing.
But in this case, I didn't make any changes.
So form is valid.
So it drops down.
This is where we would normally store the data
off to the model.
I'm keeping this really simple.
And then I'm gonna redirect with a 302 to form success.
The other thing I might do is put a message in the session
so that the message makes it into here.
But I'm keeping it simple.
And the browser immediately comes back
and does a get to /form/success.
And then I return, thank you very much.
I might have pulled a message out,
as we've seen in an example,
where from the post method to the next get,
I drop a flash message into something.
But there's better ways to do that
and I'll show you that in an upcoming lecture series.
And so that's the success flow and it works great.
Now, let's take a look at what goes wrong.
So in this case, I got my form.
I put in the wrong kind of title.
It's too short.
I send a post.
It gathers up all this data, sends it along with the post.
That comes in and request.post.
And so now, the form comes back
and now form is valid as false
because I've violated a rule.
Now, the interesting thing is in this form object
is not only the old data, but also all the error messages
because at this moment, it has constructed a form object
and part of the form object is error messages, okay?
So if it's not valid, let's make a little context, okay?
Let's make a little context and pass that in
and then out it comes and at that point,
that form as table is gonna print out all of this stuff,
all those error messages come back.
So I render it back.
Now, I render it back and then of course you can submit it
and maybe get to a success.
Now, there is one sort of interesting question
about this page which I have asked
a Stack Overflow question about
and I'm not sure I'm ecstatically happy about it
and that is this pattern is exactly
how Django wants you to write it.
It wants you to write this
and if you'll notice, I'm doing something
I told you not to do.
Django is telling me to do something
that I don't wanna do and that is return a 200
at the result of a post.
So I got a post.
Now, the key thing is that the thing
that everyone will agree on is once you store data,
you have to return a redirect
and so the Django people who've done this for years,
they consider it okay to return the 200
and a page after a post if no data was changed.
Now, the problem is if you hit refresh on this,
you're gonna get the weird funky message
but this is how Django works
and so I don't know what to tell ya.
I can write my forms differently.
It's a few more lines of code in here
and I've written that and I've made it so that
I pass the error message and I serialize the form
and put it in the session and do something
but I'm not gonna fight city hall on that one.
I'm just gonna say if Django thinks it's fine,
the thing we do agree on is if you're gonna return a 200,
don't return a 200 after you've saved data
'cause then you'll double save the data.
Like you'll double commit a transaction,
you'll do a transfer, you'll double order,
you'll do whatever but in this case,
all we did is looked at the data, came back
and then sent back an error message.
So you can look at the stack overflow
where I sort of argue for a little bit.
So this has been a long lecture series.
We talked about HTML, we talked about HTTP,
how get and post are different ways of doing it.
We've talked about the idea of you can't,
how to fix the refresh.
We talked about cross site request forgery, CSRF
and how Django handles CSRF and then toward the end here,
we've talked about how to define forms in Django
to sort of outsource all that HTML generation
and how we do validation.
Now, there's much more to learn on this
and we're going to learn more of the features
of form objects as we go forward
and build increasingly complex applications.
(upbeat music)