So now that we've introduced CSRF conceptually, let's talk about how we actually implemented
running in Django. So if you remember, I didn't really point this out too much when we went through
it. This was my first form where I showed you how data could be transported to the server using a
POST request. If you look at the top, I have this little annotation, @csrf_exempt, and there's a
little import above it in the views file. And what I was basically telling Django is don't blow this
up because I'm not handling CSRF properly. So what we're going to do is we're going to do the exact
same view, except we're just not going to have that little thing. So we'll call this one fail form,
and we're going to throw out a form, we're going to press submit. Everything looks fine. The only
difference is is I did not turn off CSRF processing. So on a POST request, CSRF processing is on by
default, which means that we have to do something explicitly when we're making POST forms. But I
didn't do it yet, so this is what happens if you don't do it. So you get a, you know, you get a
form and you press the, you know, type some stuff in and you hit submit query, and boom, you get this
forbidden message. That's a 403. So among all the HTTP responses, we've got 200, which is okay. We
got 302, which is moved, and we got 404, which is not found. 403 is you're not getting this page,
but not because I don't have it, but because you're not authorized to do it. So this is it
aborting and stopping the POST. So it comes in, it looked up the session, and everything looked good,
except the CSRF did not match. Now, this, we are a legit server, so what we've got to do is we've
got to actually add the CSRF to the POST on the way out, okay? So this is the exact same POST,
and I'm doing this kind of at a low level, and I'll show you, we'll show you a much easier way
to do it in a minute. So we have an input hidden. I just happen to know that CSRF middleware token
is the proper name for it, and I'm just gonna have a placeholder, which is underscore underscore token,
and so then what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna clock to that middleware, CSRF, get token.
Now, that token is probably just a number sitting in the session, but I don't need to know that. I
just say, hey, give me the token for the current request. Request is, of course, all that data
that's coming in. It's got the sessions, got everything else in it. So hey, give me that token.
This is a big, long string, which is really just a big, long, random number, a big, long, random
string, and then what I'm gonna do is take whatever that big, long, random number is,
and I'm gonna replace this little bit with a stir, a simple replace, and then I'm gonna send that out.
So this time, when we go to that page, you'll see that now we have an input type equals hidden,
name equals CSRF middleware token, and then the big, long middleware token, whatever that is,
and then now when we submit it, it bundles up both the guess and the middleware token,
and it actually bundles up to submit as well if it's got a name, and sends that in as post data.
So now when it dumps out, you see, oh, well, you got guess equals 42 and CSRF middleware. Now,
by the time it's got to this point, we're not really doing the checking here. The checking was
done before the view started, and so if we go back to the view here, the checking is done
before it gets to here. When you're dispatching from urls.py to this, and it says, hmm,
you didn't tell me not to do CSRF, and it's not done properly, so I'm gonna blow you up.
So if it's gonna work, it's already worked. The fact that we've come in here and we're dumping
this stuff out of the post, that's just sort of like we see it, but it would have blown up before
it would have even got to our code at that point, but we do get it and see it as post data.
We don't need to, because by the very fact that our view is running means that the CSRF
processing has been successful. And again, the rogue system has to somehow get its hands on this,
the actual number of the CSRF, and that changes every time you log in, and literally it could
change every hour or so or whatever. And so it's a hard number to guess, and it's a hard number to
get your hands on. Now, that manual thing is not the easiest way to put this in. There's an easy
way in CSRF. You simply say, so here's our form, here's our slash form. I do all the stuff I want
to do that I want to do, and then I use the code. It is called template tag. When you have CSRF
enabled in your Python, you have a template tag of CSRF underscore token, and that emits the input,
the type equals hidden, the write name, and all that stuff. So you, as the developer using templates,
you don't have to know anything about that. And so that's how we do CSRF, and the only other thing
we got is guessing game, and then we're going to pass a message into that, and we're going to do
that in a bit. We're going to use this for a whole bunch of little examples, so kind of remember this
particular guest.html template. But the key right now that we're talking about is the fact that we've
got this CSRF token in. Now, I'm going to write a bunch of guessing games, and these guessing games
I'm actually going to start checking the guesses. So I'm going to have a function in this view
that's called check guess, and it's pretty simple. It returns a string or false. If the guess is an
actual non-false thing, we check to see if it's too low, too high, or right on time, or if it
doesn't convert, if this guess throws a trace back, well, then we'll say bad_format = guess,
and then just because it probably came from the user, we're going to escape it and then send that
back. So whatever it does, we're going to send back a nice little message going back. And so here
is a simple guessing game that we're going to do, and so we're using a class-based view this time.
Of course, we extend the class view, and remember how it works is it's not just a function. We
actually have two methods. One is a get request, and the get is called when we're receiving get
request, and the post is called when we're receiving a post request. This alone is one of the nice
reasons to do this. You don't actually have to say if it's a get, do one thing, if it's a post,
do another thing. We just have two methods, and Django properly routes the requests in,
okay? And so this is going to be a form post. So on the get, we just render with no messages.
We render with no messages, and we have a CSRF token that goes out, so we just render it.
Then we'll click the button so that this render right here will produce this page. Then we type
in the guess of 42, and we hit submit query, and then that bundles it all up, including CSRF,
and goes to the post. Now the CSRF, as long as we put it in that template, we don't have care,
because before that post method gets activated, CSRF has been processed, and we get a 403 if the
CSRF isn't right. So if we go back up here, and you don't put this in, and you run this code,
this CSRF token, you don't put it in, then it's never going to make it to the post. I mean,
it blows up in route to the post if the CSRF doesn't happen. But we've got CSRF, and it's
all automatic, we just throw that one line inside of our form, and that's all we've got to do. So
we put 42 in, we hit submit query, pass the CSRF, it comes in, so we grab the post data,
the guess from the post data, we call my little check message, check guess, that's going to give
me that little message, whether it's too low, too high, or some kind of other mistake, and then I'm
going to pass in a context, the string message has that string, and if then we go, I have it down here,
no, have it up here, so then the message comes out. So this, you'll notice I've surrounded this
by an if, so this message is false or not present, then it doesn't put anything out. But if it is,
it actually puts the message out. And so out comes the guess, and so this is what it looks like when
we do a get request, we see this, then we're going to see all this stuff, we're going to type our
number in, we're going to hit submit query, and then it's going to fire up a post request.
And so then it's going to come back into the post request, it's going to get the guess from the post
data, it's going to check it, and then it's going to pass the message in, and so the message is going
to come out here, and then we're going to return that page. And so you're going to see something like
congratulations 42. So that took, that was part of the post, and so we now have made a successful
guessing game. So next we're going to talk about, just when we get something working,
there's always something that we have to say, oh, but there's a little detail that we forgot about.
So up next, we'll talk about post and refresh, which is a little problem that we're just going
to have to fix.