>> Hello everybody and welcome to our lecture on Cascading Style Sheet, CSS.
Of course, this follows right on the heels of our HTML lecture.
And I'm gonna use a bunch of examples from webapplicationsforeverybody.com.
And you can just bring these up in your browser.
I love to place everything that we talk about in the context of the request
response cycle, cuz that's the whole web applications for everybody.
You, of course, are out here, you do a click, it sends a request, a HTTP request.
It maybe talks to a database, get some stuff back, send some stuff back.
This is the request response cycle right here.
And the thing that comes back is HTML.
And then that is parsed, put into the document object model.
And the thing that you then see, the pixels you see on your screen,
are from the document object model.
So that's what we've been doing so far.
And so far, in that HTML lecture, we just talked about this.
What the format was when you parsed the response.
So what we're gonna talk about today is we're gonna talk about,
in addition to that, we're gonna go and pull another file, a CSS file.
CSS, and that is gonna inform the document object model.
And it's gonna change how things look out here.
And so we'll have some CSS in the HTML, but we'll also have some CSS in
separate files that make separate request response cycles.
But so we're gonna be putting files like our HTML files in here and
our CSS files in here.
So we're gonna be serving them a little bit.
But mostly what we're worried about is sort of the form,
how to make the DOM look pretty, and that's sort of what CSS is all about.
So in addition, I would like you to install
this thing called Web Developer from Chris Pedrick.
Chris Pedrick has been doing this a long time,
before there were even developer consoles in browsers.
And it's funny that developer consoles don't do what this does.
And it, I don't use all of its features, but
it has some wonderful features for CSS, in particular turning on and
off various styles.
And so it's a great way to sort of dig through CSS issues,
in addition to the web developer console.
And you can do a lot of sort of fine debugging, but
there's some real nice stuff with web developer.
It's just a plug-in for your Safari, or your Chrome, or
your Mozilla browser, or whatever.
So please install that, I recommend it, and
some of the assignments actually require it, so.
So like I said in the HTML lecture, the HTML started out with,
we were just amazed in 1995 when we could see a page with a gray background and
blue links, and it was lists, long lists of links.
And the links turned purple, and we would click on a link, and
another page would come up and we're like, holy mackerel, this is the future, right?
And we were so happy.
And our curiosity was peaked, we did interesting things.
But in the 10, 15, almost 20 years since all that, it's become a business.
And in business, the look and feel for the average non-nerd user,
they don't care that there's a request-response cycle.
They just want to do a thing, talk to their friends, or look up information.
Or whatever.
And so the CSS is in the middle of this time frame.
The ability to precisely lay things out and
make pages beautiful became super important for
the web to take its sort of leap into commercial dumb.
So if you look at the Yahoo web page, for example, this is just a screenshot,
I took a while back.
They do studies as to how much white space is in between those two pieces.
And they'll add a pixel and take away a pixel and they'll see how the revenue goes.
And so these user experiences, these visual looks and
feels are highly tuned and highly sort of taken care of.
And so CSS needed to be able to precisely have a pixel perfect layout in
every browser.
And so CSS is a very, very precise thing.
HTML has become precise, but we don't wanna do our markup and layout in HTML.
I showed you tables previously, and
in really early versions of HTML we used tables to create look and feel.
And that was never good.
So one of the things you can do with the Chris Pedrick web developer plugin is you
can show a page without CSS.
And what you should expect when you see a page without CSS is it's
sort of beautiful even without CSS.
It's beautiful in a logical, in a structure.
And so here's my web applications for everybody website, right?
It's got some cool stuff.
It's got these little things that go over there.
It's got the little border.
The color's gray here and it's a little lighter gray and
this wraps around and it looks really awesome, right?
Well, turn CSS off and
you should still see a page that you could effectively navigate.
It's like going back in time to a simpler time of, okay, I wanna see this.
This is really a list of links at the end of the day.
And there you go, it's a list of links.
And the default is, I've already clicked on lessons, so
lessons is purple now.
And here's this video and if you scroll up and down on this,
I mean it's really fun to go to a website and turn CSS off and
see how good their HTML developers are and how pretty it is.
And so it's supposed to be pretty in a simple way.
And what's nice about this is it really leads to good accessibility,
meaning some people do not see the graphics, they hear the page read to them.
And this way, this is how it's read and the simpler and more beautiful and
elegant your HTML is, the easier it is for
a person who has reduced visual ability to understand your site.
And that is, I remember the joy of hearing from people who were using
the web end gopher in the early days, how they all of a sudden could go anywhere and
see anything and do anything in a way that visually impaired people could never
do for like hundreds of thousands of years and it's joyful.
And then what happened was is we ended up with this really nasty markup and
then they're like, it was like the web was simple and they loved it and
then the web became ugly and nasty and HTML became nasty.
And they're like, the world is horrible because now you go to all these cool
websites but I can't go to these cool websites cuz I'm visually impaired.
And now we're back, we're back to that, we're back to beautiful HTML, simple HTML.
And then beautiful web pages and CSS is the, okay,
I think I've done enough advertising for CSS and accessibility and beautiful HTML.
So ultimately, if you look at how this thing is assembled in your browser,
there is an HTML page that is pulled down and then there is CSS.
Sort of both inside the document, sometimes there's CSS in the document.
If you look at this, not that it matters, there's a little bit of CSS in that
document and then a whole bunch of other CSS that brings all the beauty to this.
Sometimes it even takes some JavaScript and whatever.
And so we understand that the HTML does not have the beauty in it,
the beauty comes from the CSS.
And that is part of what we try to do is learn CSS.
So if you're gonna be like a coder and you're not gonna be a graphic designer,
you still need to know enough CSS so that you don't write horrible HTML, so
that you know what a really good CSS developer is capable of doing on your behalf.
And on large projects, including like Sakai Project,
which is a open source learning management system.
This allows separation of concerns.
And you can have people that specialize in the back end and the HTML.
And then a web designer can, the web designer, so
if you think of the developer usually, there's a back end.
And then they generate, from the back end, they generate the HTML.
And then the designer will build the CSS.
The designer will often have skill enough to sort of tweak the HTML if
the developer built bad HTML.
So they kind of meet in the middle of the HTML with the developer mostly being
responsible for building the back end developer.
And then the front end designer can then tweak the HTML a little and
then tweak the CSS.
And so the HTML is where the back end developer and
the front end developer come together.
But it means that you can, it means that you can have lots of people working and
you can develop highly specialized skill sets in larger projects.
I know that my skill set is in this side, I am not skilled in this side, right?
I can clunk my way through CSS and everything that you'll see is my CSS.
And you'll be like, whoa, that's not very good.
And if it even looks pretty of mine, I'd probably use bootstrap.
And I cheated and found a CSS framework, and I didn't build it, I just did it.
Now there are people who are smart enough to build bootstrap.
That's, and they can build such gorgeous websites.
And my job is to build beautiful HTML that then they can add CSS to and
make it super gorgeous.
So the CSS basic syntax is different than HTML, right?
HTML is less than and greater than.
CSS has curly braces.
I don't really know who invented the first.
I should find that out and go videotape that person.
But it has curly braces and semicolons, so
it kind of looks like a little bit of C. And it's really a set of rules.
And it's not sequential, although the order does matter,
because what comes later has more importance than what comes earlier in CSS.
But it's not like code that gets run.
And so the anatomy of a CSS rule is that there is some kind of a selector.
And in this case, the simplest selector is the tag that we want to affect.
We want to affect the body tag.
Now, there's only one body tag.
But you could have a P for a P tag and say, I would like to do this to all P tags.
And so it's implicit, kind of like SQL, in that a body tag means for
all body tags.
There's an implicit loop for the whole document.
And we'll see how to reduce that later to it, so
it's not always the whole document.
But for now, a tag there by itself means every tag in this document.
And then there's a series of rules, and so this is really when to apply.
This is sort of what aspect, and there's a whole list of aspects that you can have.
And then what you want to do, I want to make the font size 100%.
I want to use Arial, and then sans serif, etc, etc, etc.
Holy mackerel, my little pen is undoing itself.
And so then these end in a semicolon, and you can have a bunch of these, right?
You can have just one, you can have more.
But that's the basic idea, is a CSS rule is, go find a part of this document and
paint it.
I like to think of this as like, go find a thing and
then run a paintbrush over top of it, that is this paintbrush.
That is the paintbrush that you go select a piece of the document and
then paint it yellow or paint it bold or whatever.
That's kind of how I think about it.
Now, I'll admit, I'm really a very weak CSS developer, and
I need a cheat sheet, and if I'm gonna do CSS,
having this even a single page cheat sheet is super helpful for
me just cuz I don't use it all the time.
And so the attributes like background color and the border dash bottom,
for me, they're all very self-explanatory.
They're really easy to understand.
Or if you don't understand them, you just Google and you go Stack Overflow.
But for me, I'm like, is it border bottom or bottom border?
I just can't remember that stuff, and so
I just have to have a cheat sheet whenever I work.
And this is one cheat sheet that I happen to like.
And these are the kind of properties that we're gonna be playing with.
Color, the background color, how to align it vertically,
how to align it horizontally.
Padding, which is space on the sides, etc., etc., etc.
So there's just tons of CSS properties.
And there's tons of great documentation on each of these CSS properties,
with little samples all over the place.
And I have my own samples as well.
Then I'll do some recordings and
show you walk you through line by line on my sample code as well.
But this is the kind of stuff that we're gonna play with in CSS.
So up next, we're gonna talk about how we connect CSS and HTML together.
[MUSIC]