so welcome back now we're gonna now we're gonna take a look at some more examples we're not going to
the one thing we're not going to look at is exactly how this navigation bar works at least until
a little bit later so the next thing we want to take a look at is how fonts work and there's a
couple of ways that you can put fonts into a file there are default fonts that every browser is
required to produce like serif sans serif monospace cursive and fantasy and so they you don't exactly
know what's going on but they're they're often used as fallback fonts and and so you can have
those there are any any font that is on the system like ariel or helvetica and so if you're going to
use ariel not all systems have ariel although most of them do these days and you have to have more
than one font now another thing that's really common these days is to include a font somehow
you find out about a font and here's a lotto font and you go look it up on the web and you find oh
include this and so i included this link because i found this really cool font lotto and this extends
the browser the browser then learns about this font it downloads the font caches them and keeps
them in the browser and then i can make a font that's lotto but i just in case i'm off the
internet you know and i can't download this thing i have sans serif as a fallback for lotto so lotto
is a fancy font etc etc so there's there's ariel and built-in fonts etc etc and so that's
how fonts work colors there's a lot of cool stuff about colors there's a couple different
things ignore the nav for the moment i'm just using span tags here there's some default colors
in the earliest of browsers these days we have all these fancy ones and you can go look these up and
you just google for html colors and there's a bunch of names and then they're consistent across
browsers but there's there's like 12 or so really solid names that are in all browsers since the
beginning of time but more modern browsers have a better palette of colors although really good
graphic artists want to have a much better control of colors and so this is the pound sign says that
this is a hexadecimal number and it's got two digits hex means they go all the way up to f so
f is an a through fr numbers 8b is the red level 45 is the green level and 13 is the blue level
and so this is a brownish color and then there's what's called websafe colors where you just have
this ends up being 88 44 11 but it sort of reduces the number of potential colors if you
were mixing colors from various sources and so and then in html5 you can see this color picker
when you have a form which we'll talk about in a bit it's a color of color form for modern
browsers and then you can pop up with this button a color picker and i've got a little
thing to print out what the color would be and so it just when i pick the green it basically puts
00ff that's red green and blue it puts that in into this thing which then the program could use
you know it could read this or javascript could read it or a server code could read it but right
now we're just kind of playing with the picker and we pick a different color and so that that magenta
is all the red none of the green and all of the blue and orange is all the red some of the green
and none of the blue so those are all just really strong colors and so that's what's called an html
color picker anchor tags um in the old days anchor tags were kind of funky they were blue if you hadn't
yet visited them and they were uh purple if you had visited them and so this one i've obviously
clicked on and so we have a whole series of styling mechanisms that we can have um if we take a look
at these um i have put these all in the inside of an id tag of cool so this is this is basically
saying find the id tag of cool and then style anchor tags to make them a font weight bold
so let's take a look here so i got one one paragraph that has this this one here and then
i have a paragraph with an id tag of cool and that's basically so i don't have to style usually you
wouldn't say i'm only styling the anchor tags inside of um you know if i'm only i'm only
staying staying the anchor tags inside the a pair uh a tag that has an id of cool but that way i can
have the default on this one that was my way of keeping the default so normally you would just say
a so a uh links is red if it's visited it's orange and so this one's been visited so you
don't see the red it means it's unvisited um hover you can change it so you notice when i hover in
the text decoration goes away the underscore goes away and i have a color of text font color of white
and a background color of navy and then there is one last moment and i click on this one and i will
click there's one last moment that's really hard to catch and that is the moment of active if it the
web was slow and you clicked on it then it would tell the user in the old days this made more sense
that it would turn red and then blink away i don't know if we'll even see it it kind of saw you sort
of saw it so there was a color while you click on it yeah there it was um you might not see it
in the in the screen but that's what the uh that's what the um the active means is you've clicked on
it but it hasn't yet been retrieved and then like a moment letter the whole page goes away
another thing we can do is we can play with images okay and so um here is an image um
one of the things that's really fun to do with images is float them to the right or float them
to the left and then what happens is is that the uh image the text is drawn around the image so
it wraps around the image and you'll notice where i floated this left oh i kind of got rid of
everything i floated it left before the h1 and so what happens is the h1 top of the h1 in the top
the image i'll line up and then all the text afterwards um all the text afterwards wraps around
it and so you'll notice that i've got the image first and then the h1 second and that what the
float sort of disconnects the image from the normal line of flow floats it over and then takes
this next thing and the next paragraph and use saves the space for the image and shoves everything
shoves the margin over so that it comes over here now once you start floating images you
got to learn about this clear equals all because if we want this next paragraph like this one we
want to we want we don't want this paragraph for whatever reason to be on the image now if it goes
far enough you see this this this paragraph here moves back to the left margin and then this next
one starts there but if if the browser is wider and the text is there's not so much text we don't
want this to be up in here and so you say br clear equals all so between this paragraph and this
paragraph we do br clear equals all and um you can put images right in the middle of the text like a
character you don't have to have them by themselves and you can even make an image that's a clickable
link and so you can click on that image now c and css stands for cascading style sheets and so the
idea is is that the tag that's closest has more precedence than a further away tag unless you
say important okay so here we have some style um here we have a uh a body tag uh border style
of dotted red and red a border color that's red and important and border width that's five pixels
background color uh which is kind of a grayish that's that gray and an extra padding so we've
got put some extra padding um all the way around it and extra margin um and so
so if we take a look at this we take a look at this paragraph right here we see some things and
we take a look at what we've got so we've inherited this we we got a border style of color we it wants
to have a border color of green but it doesn't because um it says the border style is solid
so the border style of solid is down here in the second style tag so the second style tag has
precedence because it's closer to the paragraph and so we tried to we tried to say border color
green but that one was overridden so otherwise this would have a solid green border except that
this red important is up there and so that the red important wins and you can see it really easily
here that this was overridden and this is the one this this this border color problem the previous
one is taking precedence okay and so this is the second one and it would normally take precedence
over this one except that this important is is sort of like it it is overriding the one that's
closer so another example of closer is the style tag okay and so here we go this is border this is
the we're putting this i mean style attribute we're saying border style equals dash border color
equals blue and so the border style equals the border style equals dash holds on but our attempt
to make the border color blue is overridden again by the red important right so important is up
above that okay and so this this this dashed is winning and this blue is not winning because
there is an overriding red above it i mean there's an overriding red important above it
and so if you want to override an important tag yay we override an important tag right here
we basically say i want a border style dashed come over here border style dashed and i want the border
color to be blue and this is important so now this one's closer and it says important so among all
the important ones the closest is important one wins so now we see that the border color actually
takes here and um we are overriding the far away this one got this one here from farther away got
overwritten because of this one and so you can do that now in general while i've shown you how
important works you shouldn't do too much with important because usually you're taking csss from
other places and and um you're you're you're patching it and you can end up with really
inconsistent looks and feels with with important usually when you see important it means kind of
something's wrong and you're fighting with a framework or something else so let's take a
look at some blocks um and so let's see background color why each one's colored blue
and i'm going to put some padding and a margin um and so div p and h1 sort of live in a box
you have sort of like the actual uh so let's take a look at say this paragraph right here that's
probably the thing to do this is just a plain old paragraph nothing special right there we go that's
a paragraph right there so so let's talk about the padding and the margin right so working from the
inside out there is the actual text that is and it's wrapped and so if this if i change the width
of this this whole block changes right it gets taller and narrower but at some point the in
inner part this inner part right here is uh the inner part is however large it becomes and that
in this case it's 318 by 38 pixels right and then what happens is we sort of work from the out work
from the inside out so let's i'll go down here and see the box model so the inside of this the actual
text is 619 pixels by 19 pixels and then i've asked to add 10 pixels of padding and that is between
this sort of text and the border and then the border itself has a width and i specified that
border width um right i said i want a five pixel border width and so the border width takes up five
pixels and then there is outside of that there is margin and so margin is space notice that the
padding and the text itself has the background of the block border has its own color and then
the the margin as the background of the color of the background document okay so this is the
margin here it's the color of the background document right so content padding border margin
and then but the padding inherits from the text in the box from a background
and the margin inherits from the background document
and you can have different background colors etc etc etc this is an uh oh by the way this is an
ordered list that we've got going on right here okay so that's css boxes we can change the size
of these boxes it's uh it's a little tricky so uh and so here we have a auto sizing div where
we're not mentioning anything about the height if we take a look at the box model here we see that
this one is simply you know the size of the text plus the padding plus the border plus the margin
and that's sort of how how that box gets sized you can say that you want to set the size of the box
okay so i'm going to set that to be three m's three m's is three characters um but if you look
i have too much in here and so you'll see that even though this box is three characters tall
uh it's four lines and so the three would fit but the fourth one doesn't and so just overflows
you can also so three m's it's good to set sizes and m's when you can because then if the if someone
makes the screen larger oops i didn't mean that i just wonder if someone makes this larger or smaller
now the problem is well i don't know about if we call it a problem but in the old days if you
set a height in pixels and you zoom the screen the box that where you set height and m's would zoom
and the one that you set in pixels wouldn't but they decided to make zooming work otherwise
zooming so many people made boxes in pixels that they made it so that the the zooming would pretend
that pixels are really m's so it kind of converts pixels to m's but you're really technically you're
supposed to avoid using pixels when you really mean uh characters if you want three lines don't
look at your font and say i'll make this 40 pixels in order to do that and again we still in this box
we still have uh overflowing text and so we have a couple things we can do when we want to uh change
the overflow we can tell a box that we would like the the overflow to make a little scroll bar
and so here's here's that same stuff and you can see we got a little tiny baby scroll bar
and it it didn't sort of blurp blop out of the box right and you and even if the scroll fits
you see you get little scroll bars but you can't scroll it because there's only one line there and
it fits in the box and then another thing that you can do is you can uh just say chop it off
right chop it off now one thing with some tava script you can put a little more here and that
expands the box or pops a by-log or whatever but we're not gonna worry about that for now
for now we're just saying overflow hidden means lay this out as much as you need and then you know
throw this text away it's just not there anymore like where did all this all this text go but it
doesn't show it because we told it to chop it off okay so on to the next one you can move these
things around uh this is a little messy there we go let's make this a little different okay so
so by default i'll show you the html in a second for this or maybe just do view source let's do
view source okay so if you just say div div they just follow after each other um and i've given
them border because to make them a little picture give them some border some padding and some margin
just so they don't touch each other too much so by default blocks just so i got a little border
both on all sides a little bit of space between them and a nice so they you know however big they
get this one gets bigger and i put a width on them just so that so that they wouldn't move around
and that's there's a width on it right there 10 m's 10 characters wide so they just follow each
other and then you can say okay you know this block right here this number three would lay
out right here but i have told the number three block i've told the number three block that i want
to move relative to where you would normally be 20 pixels to the left and 20 pixels uh down from the
top and so this block it lays out exactly as if it belongs right here and then we shoved it over
and moved it down and and it came over top of the number four block and so there you go and so the
the text afterwards this number four block just comes next and it's it's basically it's as if
this laid out without that without the position relative and then this came afterwards but then
we sort of just shifted it and that's why this overlaps because this corner here is where three
would have finished and with a normal layout so you got to be careful with relative i mean you
don't usually want to make it so that they uh sort of blop on top of each other okay and so now we're
in four and then we're going to look at five and six and so five is what's called fixed text and
you'll see i'm the five comes right here but because i've got this as position fixed this
is fixed relative to the window so it's 20 pixels up from the bottom and 30 of the way from the left
margin so you can see that this is uh 30 of the way from the left margin and it's uh the bottom
of it is 20 pixels up from the bottom and you'll see that that green box never moves and that is
because the fixed text is relative to the window and that's how we actually get this little link
that never goes away and so there's a link that never goes away um absolute text it's i don't know
why they call it fixed and absolute but absolute text is a little bit different it's relative to
the parent element and so in this div right here the parent element is the body tag and so when
it's saying i would like this to be uh 40 pixels from the top and 30 pixels from the 30 percent of
the way from the left that means it's relative to the body tag and so the body tag starts up here
and so this has been sized 30 from there and whatever 40 pixels down and notice that that
one goes with the scrolling right so that one goes with the scrolling and you'll also notice
that between four five and six there's like it's as if there's nothing here but if you look at the
document five and six are sitting there and that's because they are plucked out of the normal
rendering stream and so they don't take up any space between four and seven so they're
they're they're they don't count in sort of the normal layout as the page is being laid out
and so so here's number seven for example actually number eight so here's number eight
and so this is uh positioned relative with a left of negative 100 1000 pixels and so in a sense this
stuff right here has been shoved off the screen to the left and so that's that's what how we often
will put text on that nobody sees just move it to the left but it takes up the vertical space anyways
because it was just relative it would have normally laid out here but the left shoved it over there
and so that's basically uh some some layout and so uh now we're going to talk about z index
let's take a look at the source code here
and so a z index is the ability to what happens when things overlap okay and so this is a div
number one has a z index of 100 a number two has a z index of negative 100 zero is sort of the
background document and it works out pretty straightforward and i'm just moving these so
they have to lay on top of each other um you know and so you see this this one here is negative
100 so it's kind of behind everything um this one is uh positive 100 so it's in front of everything
and this number three is um yeah it's and i just put that there to be in the original document
at the with no z index whatsoever and so it's behind this thing that has a z index of 100
okay and so that's z index um like this little note way over here by the right margin says
z index is uh kind of tricky everyone tries to be on top and um you'll put z index of 100 and then
you'll find that the navigation put itself as the index of a thousand or something like that right
and um and so z index is hard to debug and hard to fiddle with but at least now you know
that z index is the when things look weird and they're overlapping in weird ways z index is what
you're taking advantage of and so now we'll take a look at kind of how this navigation works okay
and um and so here's a couple things that the navigation does uh the body of course is font
family ariel sans serif the navigation bar itself the nav that's i guess i'll do a view source on
this so we can look at the navigation bar uh the navigation bar itself this block it's a block tag
right that has a position of light gray and i've given it a height of three m so it's like
three lines and if i zoom this page in and out
right that gets bigger and smaller don't get back to 100 um it's three lines tall and i guess i
didn't mean to say ariel sans serif i did that in case someone else wanted to change the body tag i
guess um so then i have within i want ul tags within the nav and that's one of the nice things
about this nav being its own tag i can style just the ul's inside here okay and so what i'm doing
here is i'm saying uh i i don't want any uh little uh circles little dots little bullets i don't want
any of those i want to take away any padding that it has by default this is one of those things that
this ul inherits um let's go down here and take a look at this and you'll see that um
this ul right here um so what's happening is this is the things that i've said in my css and i'm
overriding some default things uh it's normally would be display uh it's a display block that's
okay um and so i i overrode the the the list type style um and continuing on uh the list item inside
of nav that's what it is nav and list item i wanted i wanted to make that so let's uh let's
inspect this guy right here inspect so uh if you look here uh so and oh and i've got a class of
back and so the i have this position absolute which is relative to the parent right here and
i have 20 pixels to the left of that upper left hand corner and so that's how this comes over here
and um and then i have a color dark blue because it's inside it's a nav an anchor tag within
an anchor tag within an li tag within a nav that's what this is saying
dark blue text decoration of none and so that's where that's where i get this color blue and no
underlines um and then this is the dot back and so i use a back class to just to push it for
position this right here and then i use the forward class to position this relative on the right 20
pixels from the right and so that's how i make the navigation bar work and css is really a
a lot of work we we learn a lot about css uh and and this is just a really short introduction
to get you a sense of what the basic mechanics of css are uh thanks for watching