Hello, and welcome to another walkthrough for Django for Everybody.
In this walkthrough, we're going to look at social login,
and we're going to use GitHub to do our login,
and we're going to use a piece of code called social login
framework, and you can read this.
This is the link documentation to social login.
You can read through all this stuff.
But I've actually, in my home, I've already done most of this.
And if you've based some of your stuff on the settings--
so if you've been using my code for a while,
every time you say manage.py, it says,
if you want to use social login, please see this file,
and which registration it's doing.
And so we're actually going to--
it's not really broken, but you'll notice.
Now I'm going to show you where these messages are coming from
and what we are about to change.
So this one over here.
So first off, where those messages are coming from
is down here deep in the settings.py by line 176.
It's going to import from GitHubsettings.py.
And GitHubsettings.py is a file, but this file doesn't yet exist.
So if you go into dj4e-samples,
you will see that there is a GitHubsettings dist,
but there is not a GitHubsettings.py.
So this blows up, and otherwise, it prints that message.
So there's where that message happens.
And so if you look at the documentation,
we're going to put the GitHub, oauth2, backend, et cetera, et cetera.
So what we need to do basically is we need to take this file.
There is a file called GitHubsettingsdist.py,
and we have to make a new empty file called GitHubsettings.py.
So create that new empty file.
And then the first thing we're going to do
is we're going to just take all of this
and we're going to paste it into it, so from the dist.
So this idea of a file with a dist name,
that means it's kind of the distribution file.
It's not the real file.
And so I'm just going to save this file for now.
And so if I go here, back here, I believe that at this point,
it won't say anything, because we have a file.
And it says we've switched to using-- it was using login,
and now it's using login social.
And so the login is a registration template.
So this was the login that you've been using
until you turn the social on.
And it has some rules that says, here's where you do the URL.
You get a form, et cetera.
So you get to set this login.
It's a long time ago that we set this thing.
But social login, if you read all the documentation,
read all this documentation, social login,
you have a different way of doing it.
So this is asking if that social auth GitHub key
has been set properly.
And that's this key right here.
And otherwise, it's not set.
So if it gets set, then it's going
to do a link to this social begin GitHub.
And this is something that's documented
in this Django framework.
So somewhere in here is the begin.
Yeah, so this is an example of how you call Google.
So you just do this social colon begin.
And this social, going back to settings.py,
oh, we got to go into the urls.py.
So let me go here and then go into urls.py.
So we do add something here.
And that is that we find-- we switch to social login.
We try to import that same GitHub settings.
And if we do get GitHub settings,
we switch to using the different template.
And you say template name and then
use that as social for our social login.
And then it prints out this little error message.
So that redirects to social login.
And we also have OAuth, the namespace social
for the social Django URLs.
Now, that social Django URLs is configured
by some of those settings.
So we have this file called GitHubsettings.py.
But we can't use GitHub yet, because we
have to get a key and a secret.
And so the instructions are right here.
So we go to GitHub, developer settings.
Now, I'm not going to show you the ones I'm
using for the projects or the samples.
But what you do is you just add a new OAuth app, mycoolappsamples.
And I give you some example things to put in here.
So actually, this home page is really samplesdj4e.com,
samples.
And then you've got to set the login.
And this is what you're going to need.
I'm only going to update it.
The application, I'm going to change this
to be samples.dj4e.com.
And then I register the application.
And now I have an ID and a secret.
Don't worry, I'm going to delete this later.
So then what you do is you go into Settings, not Settings
Dist.
And then you go in and you paste that in.
And then you paste this secret in.
I hope I got the secret right.
Yeah, this secret.
So now I save it.
So I save it.
And you go into my web tab, because this is my pay account.
And I'm going to go Samples and Reload Samples.
I'll just go over here and I'll do a manage.py check.
And I hope everything is right still.
But it's a good test.
And it is using the social login.
And it looks fine.
So I've got that.
Now let's just see what happens when I say log out.
Now if I say log in, I get this login with GitHub,
because I set that.
So if all goes well, I should be able to log into GitHub.
Now what's happening is GitHub is asking Charles Severance,
me, the logged in user, whether or not
to share the data to my CoolApp samples.
So I'm going to authorize it.
And then it's going to send back.
And then I'm logged in.
And interestingly, now it knows who I am.
It's a GitHub account.
Like if I go into-- where are we at?
Where's the menus at?
Menu.
Because that is based on that email account.
That's a Gravatar that's based on the email account.
So now I'm logged in and away it works.
So that's the basic idea.
It really comes down to create this GitHub settings.
Use the GitHub settings dist.
And away you go.
Yeah, the GitHub settings dist.
And you copy that into GitHub settings.
And then you put your real account in there.
Now I'm going to go ahead and go back and delete
this application so you can't use my keys.
Now it's not going to work anymore.
So there I go.
So I hope this was helpful to you,
that it walked you through a little bit of what
it takes to get GitHub authentication working.
I would observe that the reason I chose GitHub
is that you can do the same with Twitter,
and you can do the same with Google, but they're a lot.
They don't trust you as much.
And so you have to do a lot more work to prove to them
that you're worthy of using Google and Twitter instead
of just-- or Facebook.
Those are all much higher bars to get permission to use it.
GitHub is really easy.
So I hope this was helpful.
Cheers.