so we build a browser in Python it's time to build a web server in Python so
remember that what we've got here is we've got you know the browser is an
application and we've we've made this a Python application now that sends this
get request so we we have effectively like I said built the world's simplest
browser and that sends a get request the server does something and then it sends
the response back and now we're going to kind of change this right we're going to
assume the browser exists and it's like okay because we're going to be the server
folks right so now we're going to look in greater detail at what goes on in the
server and so here is a very very simple web server it's a few more lines than
the than the the simplest web browser because we have to put a little bit of
error checking in with some tries and accepts okay so let's let's walk through
what this code does okay let me let me change the color again to black if you're
from Microsoft and you can tell them to make a key to change the color on the on
the scribbler I'd greatly appreciate it oh and then I went down a page too okay
so we're going to pull in some more stuff from this from the socket we're
going to pull in some stuff from the socket right here and so we're going to
make a function called create server that we're going to call right down here
and it's going to print out how you're supposed to access it and then start the
server now the whole idea of the server is the server is woke up to wait for
incoming connections so the server already exists so when you start talking
to a web server that servers in that computer already the server software is
already running registering its interest in incoming requests so that's what we
do so when this Python program starts it's going to sit there and wait in an
infinite loop for incoming requests so the first thing we do is we're going to
make a socket this looks very much like the time we made it's an endpoint it's
not actually making the phone call we're remember I said this socket call is
making the phone so we're saying we're going to make a phone and it's up to us
later to decide if we're going to make a phone call or receive phone calls and
then this next thing is like to connect except this is I am willing on port 90
to receive the phone calls now it turns out there's only one program on port 90
that can receive phone calls so this might blow up you might try to do this I
mean port 9000 and if you run this twice and you can do it in two windows on your
computer the second one will blow up and say you can't have port 9000 because
another piece of software has it but as long as there's only one running away you
go and that's part of this whole try accept thing because if you run this
twice gonna blow up the second time because you cannot receive phone calls
on this server on port 9000 with two applications one application gets the
phone calls that's what socket listen says the five on there says dear
operating system if I'm busy handling one phone call you can hold on to four
more and queue them and then I'll come back and get it for you and that you're
asking the operating system to queue incoming calls don't just say you're
busy shut down if you didn't say this listen five if you were busy writing the
data for phone call one and phone call two came in and you weren't ready for it
right that instant it would just deny the phone call so that's what listen
says is dear operating system hold hold those temporarily I'll get back to you
which is how it works and then what happens is we go into this except now
this except is I'm at the phone I've registered what my number is and what my
extension is and I'm ready to pick the phone up let me know so this except is
blocking it stops and it just sits there and it can sit there forever you
know it just literally forever if nobody calls it nothing happens the next line
never exit never runs until you blow it up or the server goes down so that's
except is a blocking and the reason we do this except well we have to establish
the phone call first right so then this next line runs only when a phone calls
received so that means that we on the browser side we already connected you
know we made the phone call now we haven't sent any data yet right and so
this is just now at this point somewhere out there there's a piece of client
software that has done a socket dot connect and we have done except and our
except is succeeded in the server the connect is succeeded and we are ready to
talk so the phone call has been made now the question is who is going to say hello
and this is where the HTTP protocol solves our problem the server knows that
the client must speak first so it just does a receive now you'll notice the
receive and the send are the same function calls because it's a two-way
thing the whatever the browser is sending the server is receiving and
whatever the server sends the browser receives and they can do it
simultaneously if they can figure it out but usually you kind of like say it's
your turn to listen in my turn to send and then I'll listen and usually they
kind of go back and forth in this there's only one step you the server
listens gets the get request sends the data back and so then we're going to
read some data and we're gonna get 5,000 characters we're gonna get the whole
thing remember it's one line it has a get request in it it has the optional
parameters in it and so we're gonna split it now again we've received it as
UTF-8 we've got to decode it for UTF-16 I mean not UTF-16 unicode inside of
Python and then we split it based on new lines because the get request is on one
line then header header header header header header and then the blank line to
tell us that we're into the headers and we're only going to take in this we're
just gonna look at that first line we're not gonna do anything with it most most
servers actually like look at the line to figure out what document to send
there's a very simple server it sends the same document no matter what the
URL is all we do with the URL is we print to it print it out to prove that
we got it and then we construct a response and in this response again go
back to RFC 2616 and it will tell you what this response is supposed to look
like it sends back a 200 okay remember this is all the stuff we saw probably I
cut and pasted it from a working thing we tell it that we're sending it back in
content type a text HTML the character set UTF-8 remember I was telling you
that a blank line and then some HTML HTML body hello world body and I'm
throwing in these /r/ends which is the network's version of new lines and then
you will notice that I encode it before I send it because it's unicode inside of
Python and it needs to be sent as UTF-8 because the phone when you're in a socket
the thing that's going across the socket almost always is supposed to be UTF-8
so we encode it and and then because the protocol says so as soon as we send the
data we close the connection now remember that the client had to close
the connection too so we close it it's half closed and then the client gets all
of its data gets the indication that it closed knows it's finished all the data
and then the client shuts its side down and so there are two hang-ups it's kind
of like a phone call the person hangs up and then click you hang up now there's
you can't really keep talking but you do want to have both sides hang up and that
shutdown is what's going on and then the rest of this is all try-except for
various things so we clean up our socket so we don't have to restart our server
when our software blows up and so the rest of it's pretty simple and then so
this while one the first browser will talk and then it'll send some data and
then I'll go back and wait for the next phone call and that's what's going on
the next phone call comes in it doesn't get you sees a get request it sends the
data back then goes and asks waits for another phone call so this is an
infinite loop that sits and waits for incoming phone calls and it you know it
answers the same thing so it's like you call this phone number and it goes and
you go I would like a pizza and it says hello world and then click and then you
call it up and say I would like a car and it says hello world click and then
you say I would like to register for this class and it says hello world click
so this is not a very flexible server you will build far more flexible servers
but it's the one I could build and fit on a single page in a slide deck so to
run this if you you know you download this code and it's tiny bit of code and
you run it so you go somewhere maybe your laptop maybe Python anywhere I don't
know if it works on Python pride doesn't work on Python anywhere because you
can't actually talk to ports but let's just run this on your laptop and you
you start the server up somewhere get a hold of my sample code or download it
from here server dot p y and it's telling you this is just output from the
server and this is the moment at which it's waiting right it's waiting the
server could wait for hours at this point but I just give you this in a
print statement so you can copy that and put it into your browser so you paste
localhost 9,000 into your browser and then the server is printing that it got
a get request for the slash document from this browser that's what the browser
send I mean we're talking from Firefox browser to the little web server that we
just built now there's another a second get request that you don't even know
because you didn't ask for it and that's because the browser is built in to ask
for a URL called favicon.ico so that it can make an icon and that icon ends up
in the tab or wherever in your browser and so that's like an icon for the
website so you didn't ask the browser to do this but it's a thing browsers do and
you'll see when you're looking at your debug logs when you're building stuff
that it's a Fabico and so this this happens like blink blink and now it's
waiting again right and you could hit refresh or you can go start up a
different browser and you would see these get requests every get request
you're gonna see in your browser and your server so it's so it's working and
it works really well and you're welcome to go ahead and play with it and try it
all out so now we're gonna do is build a simple web client and then we'll talk to
our server so the other web client we may talk to data.pr4e.org this one is
gonna talk to yourself so it's this it almost looks identical right we're gonna
make a phone we're making a phone we're gonna connect to localhost 127.001 is
the IPv4 connection what's called loopback right to the same host we're
talking to port 9000 because that's where we've got our web server running
that little web server we just wrote and then we're gonna send a get request a
valid get request to this thing HTTP 10 and then two new lines and we're gonna
encode it into UTF-8 before we send it then we send it and then we just have a
loop that prints it all out and then when the socket gets closed we hit a
break and then we close our end of the socket so the server clicks the phone
and then we're no we're done with our data but we've already printed it out
and then we hang up the phone on our end to kind of clean everything up all the
way in between everything else so this is a very simple web client and so now
you can run the web server right just like we did before and instead of
talking in a browser we run this client and this client gets a header of HTTP 1
okay it's content type HTML it gets a new line and then the body and we're
done now I mean it's not a browser but it is client that's talking HTTP and so
now you'll notice that this server sort of sits and waits for incoming calls you
could run this over and over on the client run the client over and over
again right and then you would see more requests but in general the server is
destined to just sit and wait for hours potentially until a client connects to
it then at some point you'll just abort this server and then if you control C or
blow this up somehow this will fail the client will fail and it will fail it
will fail in this connect code so if you want to play with it try to run this
client without running the server and you'll see that the connect which is the
part of actually making the phone call this will continue to work which is make
me a phone on my current computer and then connect is make a call to the
remote computer that will blow up and then if you wanted to play with this you
could put some try and accepts around it say remote computer is not responding on
port 9000 that's if you blew up you put it could put a try and accept around
that but I'm not doing it because it don't fit on my slides so here is an
even simpler web client that we can use and you again you can get this code from
my sample code we don't talk to this we there's a higher level thing that so the
the previous client talked to sockets so I could show you the low level but
because we spend so much time talking about to URLs we then have a URL lib so
I'm just going to use URL lib I'm gonna and this could be a local host or it
could be whatever I'm just gonna make a four line URL lib call and so I just do
a URL open of that same URL now we're operating at the HTTP level because URL
the concept of URL is not a socket concept the concept of URL is HTTP
concept and we just get an effect what looks like a file handle to us and we
loop through it and print it all out so we run our server and the server sort of
says this and waits and then we run our client it basically hits our server and
we can see in the server window you got to do these two things in two windows
right you got to do these things in two separate windows so in the server window
you'll it'll sit and wait and then in the client window when it runs you'll
see the client will make the request to the server or blow up with the server
not running and the server will see the get request and then the data will come
back to the client so you sort of do this in in two things and you can run
the client over and over and over again and you'll see every time you run the
client the the server sees it responds and away you go and again our server
always says hello world no matter what which is delightful and classic it's a
classic so you actually can watch when you're running Django there will be a
way for you to see when you're running Django locally and you start the server
up this managed three don't do this later managed pie dot run server and
then you talk to it and you will see all the get requests and so Django when you
run it local you can debug a lot of what's going on so you see the you can
see like the favicon that it's asking for and that is no five or six HTTP
requests to produce that little Django web page and so that that will be
something that you will learn how to do and so so that sums up what we were
doing in this you know at the beginning you look at it very simply pretty soon
you'll just be looking at the developer console and it'll all make sense to you
I want you to be able to know that you can dig as deep as you want to and
understand all of these protocols that are going back and forth okay cheers