>> Hello, and welcome to another walkthrough for Django for everybody.
A big part of the first half of this class is what I call the big picture.
So in the big picture, we're trying to basically learn
the ways of a Python Django application.
A Django application, Django is an application that then you create
objects and load those objects in, and in those objects, you achieve your web application.
And so this is the flow where the request response cycle.
So we've got a browser on the left-hand side.
We've got the internet, very tiny in the middle.
And then we've got Django, which is running in a Linux server and
a whole bunch of files that you either have or will be editing.
And the big flow is that the user requests a page in the browser,
which gets routed into your application.
And your application may read database data or whatever, produce some output.
And then send it back to the browser where the browser looks at the response and
shows it to the user, the request response cycle.
That is the essential engine of browsers and the internet.
Now, this picture may be the best way for you to think about it.
Or you may also just think about it as a set of folders and files.
Cuz really when you're developing your application,
you're working with folders and files.
Now the screenshot I'm showing you that has a folder autos, hello, home, my site,
polls, site, is not like at the very beginning.
At this point it has several applications and several folders.
It might be a little bit easier to understand the big picture when we think
about it from a point of view of multiple applications.
So in this particular one, their site has files in it, home has files in it.
Hello is an application, autos is an application, and polls is an application.
You may have already done them or they may be in the future.
Ultimately, in comes a request and there are parts of your application
that participate in that request.
So when your application is starting, so if your application doesn't start up very
well or it blows up or it shows the something went wrong message,
that probably means as it was reading settings.py and then the rest of these
files, there was something wrong with the file, then you gotta go fix the files.
But let's assume that things in settings.py and
the rest of the files at least are syntactically correct enough so
that the application loads.
Well, Django is a Python application that in a sense
is listening for incoming requests and those requests come to Django.
But then once it gets a request like a URL like /polls or
/polls/2 for a detail page, it looks at urls.py and
that's the one that's in my site urls.py.
So there's two urls.py, there's the polls urls.py, and that's the second one.
And then there's my site urls.py.
In the my site folder, you can see that there is settings.py, which says,
here is how I'm going to set up my Django environment and
also all the applications that I want to load.
And then for each of the applications, you're going to see a urls.py and
a views.py and perhaps as we get more advanced, the forms,
models and then even admin.py for each application.
So, other than the my site urls.py,
the rest of it is kind of replicated as often as you want.
So let's take a look at some sample code in Python Anywhere.
So here we go, I got my home directory Django projects my site.
Now, one of the things that's a little bit tricky to figure out is my site is
the overall configuration for the entire Django project.
Autos is an application, hello is an application and polls is an application.
But my site is the configuration for the project.
But really this actually starts, the first thing to start your application
is the settings.py and this is all of your configuration.
What applications, polls, home and autos are the three applications that I'm going
to be loading here, but it really starts before this.
[MUSIC]
So if I go to the web setup,
this is the configuration for djfree.pythonanywhere.com.
So if I go to djfree.pythonanywhere.com,
that routes to my application running in Python Anywhere.
So djfree.pythonanywhere.com.
And so this somehow has got a domain name and
it routes into a Linux system, but then it eventually starts your application and
routes to your application.
So from here on down, if you put something on there,
you don't really have to worry too much about the first part.
djfree.pythonanywhere.com, but you do have to worry about what you're going to,
how you're going to handle and how you're going to write the rest of this URL, right?
So I just put in a bad one and we get page not found.
And that's not like your application is running.
You requested a page that your application does not know how to respond to, okay?
Now, if you have problems, you got to make sure that your source code and
your working directory are your home directory.
And then you want to make sure that this wisky.py is properly set up, but
that was set up in the very first assignment and you shouldn't need to change that.
You got to have your virtual environment correctly set.
You got to have your Python version correctly set.
And if you have problems, you can look at the server log and the error log.
If you're really having terrible problems debugging things.
But we're not going to talk so much about debugging.
We're going to talk today about routing.
Python Anywhere starts when you hit the reload button, it reads settings.py.
The wisky config tells it to read settings.py.
And then all the rest of setup of your particular Django instance
depends on what you tell it in settings.py.
So let's take a look at the settings.py because it's the beginning of your
application.
So there's a few things.
Now one of the things is this allowed host, which in an early assignment,
I set it up so that told you to say anywhere.
And that has to do with the fact that there is some filtering going on about
whether or not it actually is going to accept any requests from the internet to
your application.
So you can put a filter in a sense.
So we're saying that the settings allowed host equals star,
we're saying don't put a filter in.
The next thing it needs to do is where to start in terms of what applications need
to start.
Now some of the applications are built in applications and
other applications are applications that you've added.
So you'll add an application and it'll tell you to add a line to this.
Then there is some configuration about middleware, we'll change this later.
But then it says, load up the URLs for the overall application, okay?
And we'll see where this is in a second.
So it's like, load up all the URLs for the whole app.
When it says root, what it means is anything after djfree.pythonanywhere.com/.
That top part is the root of your application's URL hierarchy.
And then we set the database up and then some other things, but that's about it.
So this line here that says mysiteurls, well,
that is in effect importing another Python object and
then running it, doing a Python import of this.
Now mysite, mysiteurls.py, this is what basically sets up the global URL routing.
Or it doesn't have to be, but for all intents and purposes,
it's the part right after the slash.
So if I say right after the slash here, it is consulting this urls.py.
And it's got a list of URL patterns.
If it starts with admin, if it starts with polls, if it starts with hello,
if it starts with autos or starts with sites, I know what to do with that.
And the second, these other parameters are what to do with those things.
What do you do if the URL, the root URL starts with slash polls, right?
So right after the slash, well, it says I don't know what to do with that.
But if I say slash polls, it does know what to do with that.
And so it knew how to do that based on this urls.py.
So it says if it's polls, and so now I can say, I'm going to say I want to do
polls slash this slash you whatever, it will route it to the polls application.
But then the rest of this stuff has got to be properly handled by the polls
application.
And that's what it shows, it says the polls application reports back
that it doesn't know anything about LDJFJ, it just can't.
And so it's telling us the kinds of things it was looking for.
There was a bunch of things you can do to polls like polls slash owner.
Well, let's put that in there and see what it says, polls slash owner.
And I like keeping this debug message here.
It's the 404 not found message, but now polls owner is routable inside of polls.
So let's take a look at that.
So polls.url, this is basically a defined import.
It's been imported because of the settings.py that loaded up polls config.
So if we go into my site polls, so now if we take a look at our picture,
we just got done talking about the settings.py and the urls.py.
And now we're going to decompose one or more of the apps.
So we have three apps here, each one's going to have urls.py,
each one's going to have ubs.py, the rest of the things they may or may not have.
But urls is not the root url, because the my site, my site urls.py is the root url.
So we're looking inside this application to route within the application.
The part that's inside the application is after djfree.pythonanywhere.com/polls/.
And then whatever you put in there, it looks up in the urls.py in polls.
So let's go to polls, and let's take a look at the urls.py.
And so what this is, this is really saying the path within the application.
So this path right here is really /polls with nothing.
This is like /polls to, so that's a primary key.
And let me push these out a little bit, make them easier to see.
These are just comments that I'm adding to make it a little easier to see.
So this one here is urls that look like /polls/to/results.
And so what we're doing is the global my site, my site urls.py defined polls.
But then within it, we've got a primary key, we've got a primary key/results.
And we can do-- oops, not that one.
I'll just add these as samples so you can see them, pound/polls/voter,
which we just did, and then /polls/to/vote.
And these are little slugs that are going to be passed into our view.
So int pk says follow by a number, and then pass that number in.
And then the view, the detail view, is the view that we're going to use.
And that's coming from views.py, from.import views.
So I'll just say this.
I just added some comments to make it a little easier to understand.
So if we go back to our picture, if we have a URL that matches an application,
then within the application, we look at the urls.py
to figure out the within application to route to one of the views.
And so let's take a look at the views.py.
And oh, let's go back to urls.py.
So each of these names, views, this is sort of an imported file, index view.
So we're looking-- these things have to match.
Index view, detail view, results view.
It doesn't know what these mean.
It could be whatever.
And there are two kinds of views.
There is a class-based view.
Index view is an example of a class-based view.
And views.owners and views.vote are example, in this particular case,
of function-based views.
So let's go find index view, polls, index view, views.py, index view.
So see index view?
This is the code now that runs if you just type slash polls.
So all that configuration conspires to get a URL running on a server
to line 14 of your views.py.
And we're using a generic list view, which
means we don't have to write very much code.
I won't cover that in too much detail.
But the reason we use class-based views is
so that we can extend views that are provided from Django.
And so from the generic views, we're getting the generic list view.
And it turns out that all we really have to do
is tell it what template to use and what is the context object name
that we're going to put in here.
And then away we go.
And this query set is retrieving what
we're going to show in that view.
So if you go back, this is a list.
We only got one question, so it's not very exciting.
And then the only thing left in this picture is templates.
And templates are like helpers to the view.
A view can use a template.
It comes up with data to paste into that template.
And so if we take a look at the templates, polls--
now, the name of this is kind of weird, just like my site, my site.
The name of this is kind of weird.
Polls, templates, polls.
And then the index.html, this is in Django template language.
And this merges latest question list, latest question list, et cetera,
et cetera, and it loops through all those things.
So I'm not going to kind of cover all that.
I'm just looking at the big picture about how
this all works together.
Then this, when this part is all done, it returns in--
you don't see it explicitly, because it's just all
part of the generic list view.
Eventually, it returns a response object.
A response object is passed back into Django,
which is then passed down to the end user.
And so that is a quick overview of kind of the flow of things going in and out.
You may or may not have covered every single thing that is in this sample code.
But basically, I just wanted you to get us--
just go over one more time all of the stuff that's in the big picture.
Cheers.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
(jazz piano music)