Hello and welcome to my lecture on the mini-jango web server. So why did I
build this mini-jango web server? Well, the first part of my Django for Everybody
course is always about getting students to understand the nature of Django. If you
know how to use Django and you know how it works internally, it's easy to write
web applications because Django takes care of all the details of Hypertext
Transfer Protocol, HTTP. And you can read documents, tons of documents, hundreds
and thousands of pages, and write your own Python code to handle the HTTP. The
problem, though, is while Django makes it so you don't have to read any of
that, you do have to understand Django. And Django, to give you the kind of
flexibility that you need, uses a very object-oriented inversion of control, a
whole bunch of design patterns that make it so you don't have to write the whole
application. But you need to plug your work into Django. So it's important for
you to understand what the framework is and how it is that your work fits into
it. So mini-jango is the simplest possible
Django that I could write. It's under 200 lines. The mini-jango framework itself is
only 200 lines of Python, meaning you can read it, you can understand it, and you
can even change it and explore supporting additional features of HTTP. So
we're going to build both have a mini-jango and a really simple Django-like
application. So why do we use Django in the first place? Like I said, do you
really want to read RFC 7231? It is pages that's over a hundred pages and it's
detail upon detail upon detail. If you start reading it, you will realize it's
really well defined how browsers and web servers talk, but you really don't want
to read it, especially when someone else has written all the code. And all you
have to do is import HTTP request and response from Django.http and then write
a four-line function that takes as its input an HTTP request and returns an
HTTP response, and then in your code you create the HTTP response and put some
text in it and you return it, and then Django literally outside of your code
does everything else. So Django takes this super complex task and hides it
behind an abstraction. An abstraction is something you're sort of
not supposed to look past. You're supposed to just look at the interface
that it gives to you, and you're supposed to express your logic and then plug it
in at the right place to create a rich and HTTP compliant web application, and
Django handles all the details, and there's lots of them, thousands and
thousands of little detail. But with all abstractions, it's a good idea to
understand the shape of the abstraction that you're dealing with, so you can kind
of have some predictability as to when you make a change to your code, how is
that? And then Django says do this, override this method, you know override
the query method, all that stuff, you have to kind of understand what's
going on behind the scenes. And so my hope is is that if you can understand
mini Django, you'll better have a chance, it'll have a much better chance of
understanding the real Django. So in my class I use this thing I call it the big
picture, and on the left side is a browser with a document object model that
deals with HTML and CSS, and JavaScript, and intercept user actions, and then
sends the request response cycle into a server running somewhere on the internet.
There's Django and Linux, and there's urls.py and views.py and forms.py and
templates.py. And literally the first half of any Django class I teach
really is designed to understand this picture, and it's a little complex. So
what I like to do is I like to take mini Django, which I've written, and the HDB
server part of mini Django is under a hundred lines of code, meaning you can
look at it. So it's a web server that responds to a request and sends back a
response, and then we have pseudo application code, the urls.py which
handles the routing activity, chooses the right view, and then sends the request to
the right view, gets a response back from that view, and then urls.py forwards that
back to HDB server which then formats it in the right way for the network
protocol and sends it back to the browser. And if you look at how Django
itself works, it's just a more flexible and more rich and more intricate version
of this little thing that I call mini Django. So if you check out mini Django,
you'll see that it really is just four files and some documentation. The run
server.py loads the mini Django library and loads the path router and urls.py
and starts the HDB server. There always has to be a process listening on the
port to accept the connections. The web server is the library, the framework. It
is Django. It's just tiny, so I call it mini Django. It listens for incoming
service requests in a Linux process or a Windows process. Then when it gets a
request, it parses the network protocol part of that request. Then when it's got
it right, it passes the request to urls.yoururls.py for routing between the
views. Then the view produces the HDB response object, and then urls.py sends
that back to the HDB server. And then it sends it back to the browser when the
HDB server sends it back to the browser using the HDB protocol correctly. The
urls.py, much like any Django applications urls.py, it looks at a path
in the HTTP request object and then chooses a view function. And views.py is
a set of functions that capture the functionality of your web application.
Each function takes an HTTP request as its input and produces an HTTP response
for the output. So to get started, you can download the source code from GitHub
into a folder using either get or zip. GitHub, if you look at the code button
in GitHub, it gives you an option to download a zip, which means you don't
have to install git and you don't have to do a git checkout. And then you can just
file the readme instructions. If you have Python installed on your computer,
you say, "Python run server.py," and then you navigate to the localhost colon 9000
in your browsers, and you're interacting with this little server that's running
on a process on your computer. Taking a look at the source code, the views.py
looks a lot like Django's views.py, at least in the beginning in the simplest
views, where each view is a function, takes as its first parameter a variable,
I call it req in this situation, of type HTTP request, and is expected to return
an HTTP response. So if you look at it, it creates the HTTP response object. Again,
the definition of HTTP response came from Minijango. And the res.headers allows us
to set headers, then res.write creates the body of the response, and then we
return that response, which then we turn back over to Minijango to send back.
The urls.py in Minijango looks a little bit different than the urls.py in a real
Django application, because I didn't want to create, if you look at the urls.py in
a real application, it's really a table of routes, and I just made it an if-then
else, so that you can see it's not that different than what the table of routes
really is, and you might decide in your mind that this is a little cleaner and
elegant. The purpose of urls.py in Django and in Minijango is to look at the
path and choose a view, and then cause that view to be executed. And you see at
the end, if it can't find a view, it sends back a failure view with a 404 not
found. So up next, we're going to do a simple demo of downloading, installing,
and running Minijango. So here's the demonstration of Minijango for my
Django for everybody class. We've got to start by going into GitHub and taking a
look at my Minijango repository. You see GitHub.com/csev/mini_jango is where we
find the code, and in here we have a readme and then four source files, and
this readme tells us what we're going to do. We're going to start by downloading
this code and then running it, and we'll go through this in a bit. So there are
two ways that you can install this. If you have Git, find some folder, do a Git
clone, and grab Minijango. If you don't want to install Git or you don't know
how to use Git, you can just grab a zip file because GitHub is really nice, and
that's how we're going to do it. Under this code button, there's a thing called
DownloadZip, and so that's just going to download it, and it just downloaded it
into my downloads folder. So I'm going to click and see here's my downloads
folder, and on Windows it's a little trickier when you go into your downloads
folder. It hides this .zip. The Mac is pretty easy. I think on the Windows
you kind of have to right-click and extract it, but on Mac you just double
click it and it extracts it into real files. So now we see the actual files, and
so these files, Minijango, Readme, RunServer, they're all the same files
that were you got on GitHub. So now you're kind of done with with GitHub, okay?
So there's the downloads file, and now I'm going to start a terminal, and in
Windows this is like a command shell. In Windows you would type "cd" to see the
current working directory, and in Mac and Linux you say "pwd" to see the current
working directory, and my downloads are just in a subfolder underneath my
home directory, user.csev, and if I do an "ls -l" you'll see that I've got that zip
file that was downloaded, and then a folder with Minijango main. So I'm
going to go into Minijango - main, and so now if you look at the working
directory you see them in my downloads folder, I'm in Minijango.main, and as a
matter of fact if I do an "ls -l" in this folder you see the
exact same files that you see here in downloads, and so I'm going to minimize
that for now, and away you go, and so if we go back to the readme now, it says
"python run server dot py" so I'm going to copy that, and so what this does is it
starts the Minijango server. If this was Django on your laptop you'd say Python
manage.py run server. If this was Django on Python anywhere you would go and
reload your web server. Whatever this does is it causes it to start up and
listen on a server port. So I have this thing starting on 9000, higher numbers
tend to be used for development, lower numbers like 80 or
443 are using for production, and now I can go and grab this URL localhost
9000 and I can start a browser. Here's a little baby browser. Now I'm going to
keep these up at the same time, I'll come back, okay let's go back to my browser,
go back to this window, and I'm going to go to localhost 9000. As a matter of
fact before I do that I am going to turn on the web developer tools and watch the
network tab, and now I'm going to go to localhost 9000. Okay it's all clear. Oh
wait a sec, I don't need all that stuff. Okay so what we have here is we have a
what? Something went wrong. I don't know what went wrong. Maybe it's doing a head
request for all I know. Okay so I've played around too long and something
went wrong. I'll figure that bug out later. Okay so I now go over here and I
hit ask for localhost 9000 and it does a request. You can see it down here. Let's
move this up a bit so I can see it better. So it does a request and the
response is this HTML and I can see it in source code form or I can see it in
rendered form and I can look at the headers. It sent these headers in. The
request headers. So the interesting thing is is you can see this debug. Let's make
this a little just a little bigger. There we go. This thing just waits right? Oh
let's go up to here. It waits, started the server, and now there's a process
running on my computer that's hooked up to server 9000 waiting for something to
happen. I'll show you this code in a minute. So it's just debugging. I wait
for the next request. I receive a get and that's the same as this get. There we go.
That's this get to slash. It's an HTTP 1.1. It's a get request and then these
are all of the headers that are being sent and if you look down here at
request headers you see all of them. Every one of them. Cookie, pragma. Those
are being sent to the web server. The web server is receiving them on a socket
connection and then parsing that and so then it runs the code and this router
will talk about the router in a second. It says oh I got a slash path which is
slash is there's nothing here. It's after the 9000. There's nothing after the 9000.
There's slash path. Then it goes to the view and then it gets back from the view a
response. Then it sends the response headers. The only one we're really
changing is the fact that this is an HTML request and then it sends 217
characters of the body output. So this is the body output and the web
server sent 200 I'm guessing that's 217 characters and then it goes back up and
waits for the next request. Now it turns out the next request is rapidly
forthcoming and that's because it's requesting the favicon okay and the
favicon is it's trying to figure out what this icon is supposed to be. So if
you look at like let's go back to this here you can see this DJ is a favicon
and the little octocat that's a favicon and it's trying to figure out what
favicon to put on localhost 9000 but I don't have the capability to serve a
favicon so the favicon is a 404 not found so it's like hey I want a favicon
give me a favicon my browser is sending to my server give me the favicon and I
route the path to favicon and it blows up with a 404 and if you look at the
response you see the response is this 404. Let's look at the headers look
at the response headers we got a response status of 404 and we got that
it's an HTML page and those are the response headers but the 404 is the
thing that tells the browser that I don't I can't find this path that's the
path I've asked for and I can't get it and the browser is perfectly happy with
that and just doesn't put up a favicon for us. Okay so now what we're going to
do is we're going to do another request and it tells us to add /DJ4E and now
it's still this keeps asking for the favicon wish it would stop but it
doesn't maybe I'll add favicon or maybe I'll have you add favicon support for
it so we receive the headers we've got a get for /DJ4E so if you look here
let's go back to this get request this is a get with a path of DJ4E and and
then all the headers of course and we have a valid route which you'll see
this code in a second for the routing it sends response headers it says this is a
this is a text slash plain so if we look at the response headers come back if we
look at the response headers this is text slash plain slash utf-8 so this web
server on the left and the browser on the right are participating in a
protocol and again there's all kinds of rules about the protocol HTTP protocol
we keep rfc rc stands for request for content okay this 7231 so this protocol this document
right here tells us like let's go in this document search for get the get
request and the rules for what the get request looks like are here so let's
take a look the head I think the head is what when I when it blew up it was
sending a head request because I was sort of typing and it was trying to look
ahead yeah it might be that I have to check what the head is if it was a head
but let's let's keep looking for get let's look for an example get put put
put so again I'm already in page 26 it doesn't make any sense it's a mess we
don't want to learn how to do that but somebody had to know how to do it now
I've been working with some of this long enough that I wrote this code without
having to read this the the format of the headers everybody kind of knows and
the format of the body everybody kind of knows and so I I wrote this code which
I'm going to show you in a second that knows how to do this so let's get back
and so the body output it sent 13 characters of body output let's take a
look at the response the response is a plain text it's not HTML so it's not
formatted that's just that's why it's incur your format here and so let's go
back and go to let me clear this temporarily go to JS free now this
returns neither it returns a different status code it returns a 302 status code
which is a headers and so the 302 is the status code and that's called a redirect
and then it has this additional location header and so that location header says
go somewhere else okay gotta find so this is where's JS free yeah okay so
this is this is the JS free so it did a get request for JS free boom routed all
the right places route to this path of deep JS for E in my views and then it
send a response header which says I'm gonna send you a 302 and I'm gonna send
this additional location that says go immediately grab this and so the browser
without what instantaneously went and grabbed the the the DJ for E and
retrieve that and that's what that found so let's go back to the root again clear
our our browser and now let's look at an error so let's just go to a URL that is
just junk and broken and like Django oh what happened did I blow up my code oh I
was typing too long well let's run it again I address already in use you have
to wait a little bit you got to wait because the process was connected to the
port and then the process died and tried to close it but now it still can't get
it sometimes it takes a few seconds to get it back don't worry about address
already in use don't worry about it there we go we're back so now I got to
go and I got to say missing and now we get a 404 we're sending up we got it we
sent a 404 and this looks kind of like the Django but the key thing here is it
returns a header of a 404 which is I didn't know how to route this path
missing blah blah blah blah blah blah and Django does kind of the same basic
thing right and I put a dump of all this stuff just for for yucks and then I have
a broken view which I'll show you in a moment broken this has it this has a
logic error in the Python and it blows up and the 500 error is the way that the
server indicates to us that it did not get the right kind of response from the
router or the view okay so that is our widget and let me take a look and show
you some of the source code I guess I'll make this bigger now so again I am in my
users CSF downloads mini Django main and it's got the source code and so let's
start with the simplest file and this is in a sense kind of like if you're
developing Django locally python manage.py runserver if you're developing in
Python anywhere this is like the reload application button and we have to start
this this is a process that's going to listen on a port and you do this by
saying Python run server dot py you can switch to a different port with a
parameter and then if you're going to auto grade this in Django for everybody
you've got to turn on auto grader support it adds a little extra line in
there for auto grader support and and so you've got to add this Python run
server pi 9,000 autograder but if you look at this it's sort of taken that
first parameter for the port and it prints a print statement and then it's
imported mini Django okay in mini Django there is a method which we will see in a
minute called HTTP server and that starts the server and we pass into it
the URLs URLs dot py we've imported URLs and that is our URL writer router that
is our URL router that is our URL router and so we're going to run the web server
and then in the middle of that web server it's going to route the URLs to
our application so let's take a look at the web server the mini Django itself
you'll notice it's 174 lines okay so in this we've got a couple of things we
create some data classes which these are just really lightweight objects we have
a some just some data in here the method which is get the path which is like
slash DJ4E the headers which is being incoming headers that's going to be in a
dictionary and then the body which is you know if it was a post or whatever
the response which is what we're supposed to produce and send back we have
an error code which is 200 okay normally we have some response headers and then
we have a response body and we make a little method in here that basically is
going to append to a list so we're accumulating the lines which we will then
send back to so these objects are the things that views will work with the HTTP
request response and etc so the first thing we have to do is take the incoming
request and and so the parsing of the request has to do with what the headers
look like what the body looks like and it's pretty simple the headers are a
bunch of key value pairs with this colon pattern and it followed by a blank line
followed by the body so the code splits splits the the the incoming text that
we've read from the from the input here parse request the red input we break it
into head and body and then we split the header lines based on the rule and then
we we send the headers back and we put them in the object and then we return
the HTTP request object response send we'll come back to that here's a little
patch autograder stuff here's the HTTP server okay so what you see here is web
servers have a thing where it makes a socket that's like a file handle to the
operating system that says we're gonna exchange network traffic it's gonna
connect it to local host on port 9000 and then we're gonna have listen this
five is the queue so while you're processing one the operating system if
another one arrives in that moment the it'll queue up five of them and after it
gets five that you haven't processed yet but then what it does is we're gonna
have a loop an infinite loop basically we say waiting for the next response and
then we say accept it and we get a socket which is a readable bit of data
like a file handle at that point one that you can both read and write and then
the address which we're not gonna really use so once we it sits in this for a
long time that's waiting for the next request and then it reads up to 5,000
characters decodes it because it's UTF 8 coming from the internet and then gives
us that in a big string and we print the received headers which is just a string
at this point and then we call parse request which we just looked at which
breaks it into headers turns the headers into a dictionary and has the body
figures out the method and figures out the path and returns us an object of type
HTTP request now remember that 500 error if we didn't get something a parse
request I had that error happen if if we don't have the request that we got back
from parse request like a false or something went wrong we're going to just
go to the 500 error because that's the view fail it says I couldn't parse it
I'm going to give up otherwise we got a good request and so we're going to take
the router which is the first parameter to HTTP server and that is a function
and we're going to pass the request object into the function and expect to
get a response object back from the router now if we're not getting a
response object from the router then we're gonna blow up with a 500 and this
is what happens when you see the broken and we'll see that in the view in a
moment and now we got a response back and it's got all the headers response
headers it's got the response body and then we send her back and then we shut
down the socket and then we go back up and wait for the next socket so it says
waiting for next request so it spends a lot of time waiting then it gets some
data reads it really quick processes it really quick and then goes back and
waits for the next request now if we take a look at response send this is
again doing the HTTP protocol we send the headers in the right format then we
send a blank line and then we then we go through and read the body and send all
that out and then we close it all out okay so that's response send HTTP server
response send and then the last thing we've got is there's a view fail method
and that's called for like a 404 or a 500 and it's got the request in case we
need to look at it we're dumping the request actually and then a failure
string which is kind of a you know that's just some debugging additional
clue as to what might have gone wrong we're printing now we're logging this
you'll notice that we always have this logging so we're seeing all these print
statements coming out to us that makes it easy for us to debug it and you might
even blow this code up once in a while and you get trace backs in here and so
all this does is it prints out the page let's go back to the page if you say
missing you get a 404 not found and this is just Pat printing that whole thing
what the response code is the dumping it making it pretty and so this is a way
for you to debug when things are going badly and you can either get a 404 error
or if your view is broken you'll get a 500 error okay so now let's take a look
at is router okay so router is a parameter it is in the file URLs and
it's the as the function called router so let's take a look at the file URLs
and so this is similar to Python's Django URLs dot py and we get the print
statement routing to path right so that it has got the path out of the incoming
request if it's a slash we're gonna run a function out of views see it doesn't
import a views there's a function named root in views and if it starts with slash
DJ4E we're gonna call the DJ very view if it's start if it's equal to JS
free we're gonna call that view if it's slash broken we're gonna call the broken
view now if you look at Django URLs dot py they put all this into an array of
tuples basically and in that array of tuples it's more complex than this but I
figured I would just make this a simple pattern of if LF LF LF just because
that's all that array is doing if we're gonna be very simple now if we don't see
one of these paths that our application knows about we drop into this else and
then that's where we send the 404 not found okay and so let's take a look now
at views dot py and this is a views and we're gonna import mini Django and
that's the HTTP request and response that is these two data classes oops
which are really kind of very lightweight objects so lightweight
syntax to build objects quickly and so the parameter to our view is an HTTP
request because the framework has built an HTTP request and has passed it to us
right and we are expected so if you haven't been if you've been newbie to
Python or been doing Python a long time this is Python type extensions I think
it came in Python three point five the parameter name is request colon and then
the type name this is the expected type and then the return name that's just
says that when we return from this function we're supposed to send back an
HTTP response so you could do this without this sort of syntactic fluff but
boy it sure helps for me to talk to you about what the parameter and return
value are supposed to be because that's what that line is really saying okay so
our contract is we're supposed to return an HTTP response and again that's an
object defined by the framework so we're gonna create one we're gonna set the
headers the headers are just a dictionary so they're key value pair and
we're gonna tell it the content type and again you can go look up what content
type is in the documentation and then we do a series of writes and at this
point in response object if you go back and look at it that's accumulating a
list of strings and we're not actually sending the data at this moment we are
accumulating a list of strings and then we were stern we have constructed and
filled up this response object and we send it back okay and so if you go in
here it's also being returned back up through URLs dot py back up into where's
the router come back there we go the router is URLs dot py we are getting
back an HTTP response we're checking to see if it's a good one if it's not good
we send a 500 if it is good we actually I should make that be okay so I think I
got to put a little extra line code in here so by time you're looking at it I
think this is supposed to yeah I'll put some code in here okay so then we send
that response back so we're here in the views we are returning the response it
works its way back up through the URLs back into the Django itself we get the
response and then we send it back to the browser we're almost done so we have a
series this is our application code right the URLs is just kind of to get us
where we want the DJ4E is sending back a single line of text the JS free
is sending a redirect and so we're telling it to send a code of 302 that's
called a temporary direct and we're adding a header called the location
which is where we want to redirect to so we return this it goes to the browser
and the browser immediately comes back and comes back to this DJ4E and that's
what you see when you go to slash J here let me hide this boom that's what you
see when you go to JS for eat so first you see a 302 which sends back a
location to DJ4E and then the browser in a blink of an eye without doing
without waiting for you does a get request a DJ4E because that's what it
was told to do so you return this goes all the way back to the browser the
browser sees the 302 redirect sees the location and then comes back in and
reads this code and that's how that works the only remaining view is the
broken and in this it it's not going to return an HTB response all these other
ones make HTB responses and return them this is just returning a string by
mistake it turns out I think in Django you can return a string and it kind of
makes an HTTP request for you but I was more interested in causing a 500 or
return a string the path returns that to the framework the framework receives a
string as the response and then it's not an HTTP response so we get a 500 error
and so if I go to slash broken let me clear this boom I get a 500 error so the
500 error not only is a 500 error but there is a response involved in there
right and so there's some HTML that comes back with all that stuff and so
there we go I'm sure you have questions but you can look at all this code and
you can figure it all out and enjoy it so again this is about the mini Django
web server like the smallest approximately Django web server that I
could build so that you can read and even play with it put print statements
in and again this is part of my Django for everybody class cheers